- The following is a conversation
with Andrew Scull, a historian of
psychiatry and mental health. He
has authored many books that I
highly recommend including
Madness in Civilization:
A Cultural History of Insanity
from the Bible to Freud, from
the Madhouse to Modern Medicine
and Desperate Remedies:
Psychiatry's Turbulent Quest
to Cure Mental Illness.
Andrew Scull has spent decades
studying how societies have understood
madness, how psychiatry rose
to authority, and how often
that authority was used with
false confidence and catastrophic
consequences. In this conversation
we'll trace the long arc from the
asylum era to eugenics, from
lobotomy and insulin coma
therapy to electroconvulsive
therapy, psychoanalysis,
antipsychotics, antidepressants
and the modern crisis
of mental health. It is
in part a story about the
terrifying history of bad
ideas in medicine but it is
also about the fascinating
mystery of the human mind and
about the difficult
journey to understand it.
This is a Lex Fridman podcast. To support
it please check out our sponsors in the
description where you can also
find links to contact me, ask
questions, give feedback and so on. And
now dear friends here's Andrew Scull.
Is it fair to characterize your view
on psychiatry and mental illness
as that there's a crisis in modern
psychiatry? We have made some progress-
- Yes
- ... over the past century but mostly
we still are not good at treating
mental illness either via the drugs or
talk therapy meaning psychopharmacology or
psychotherapy or as you put it
the brain or the mind route.
So let's start at the end of our
story. Let's start at where we
stand before we go into the rich history
that you so eloquently write about.
- So psychiatry is a
profession that tries to
deal with an enormously
complicated thing. The
human mind, the human emotions, the human
ability to attempt to understand the world
and in particular obviously
it focuses on people where
our common sense approach to
the world seems to break down.
People whose emotional life
is filled with turmoil,
people whose ability to
relate to others is badly
damaged, people who see things
in the world that the rest of
us simply think aren't
there. They're illusions,
they're hallucinations, they're
delusions and this is a subject that has
occupied some very clever
minds over the years
and there's no question that in the course
of at least the last three quarters of a
century there has been some limited
progress in dealing with the problems that
mental illness creates. Some of that is
confined to the milder
forms of mental distress;
the more serious forms of psychosis and
breakdown of emotional control
those are areas where I think
again there's been some progress
but it's easy to overstate how much
of that there's been. As we'll see probably
later in our conversation today the
advent of modern psychopharmacology which
occurred in the early nineteen
fifties was a serendipitous
event. It wasn't planned for.
It happened almost by accident
and it did mark in some
ways an advance over some
of the things that psychiatry
had engaged in before that
and no question for some people that
revolution and a parallel revolution
in the psychotherapeutic realm have
created some advance for
patients and we should not
minimize that. What we
have available to us
are symptomatic treatments
not cures. We don't have
a psychiatric penicillin for
any of the conditions we're
gonna be talking about. That doesn't
mean we can't do some things that
help but the help is quite limited
and it's important to understand
both the ways in which we
have progressed and the
limits of that progress and also to
understand that when we treat something
sometimes we create new
problems what we call
iatrogenic problems, things caused
by the interventions that we use.
That's true of some
psychotherapeutic interventions and
most certainly true of the drugs we use
to treat mental illness these days.
So for example in treating PTSD
we often get patients to confront
the episode -- the trauma which
provoked their distress and that is
often a very, very fraught
process and for many
patients it actually makes things worse.
For some patients it makes them better.
So that's a situation where
you could see problems
With both antipsychotics and
antidepressants, the two
main classes of psychotropic drugs that
we use, um, they're at best partially
effective and they don't work for a
significant fraction of patients who
are given them and one of the big
problems psychiatry faces is that
psychiatrists don't know in advance
who's going to respond well
to the drugs, who's
going to respond badly,
for which group of patients in
the middle the side effects and
the main effects, if that's what we want
to call them, the therapeutic effect
are finely balanced and making those
judgment calls about what to do
are very, very difficult.
Now in terms of the
crisis psychiatry faces at the
moment as I see it there are
a number of strands that point to
this. Psychiatry's diagnostic system,
that is still used -- I mean,
the fundamental basis of,
of psychiatric diagnosis today was really
first formulated in 1980 with the third
edition of The Diagnostic and
Statistical Manual of a profession --
- DSM-III
- ... DSM-III and then there's been
DSM-III-R, DSM-IV, DSM-IV-TR, and now DSM
5. Finally not with a
Roman numeral but with
with an Arabic numeral.
So they thought with DSM
5 when they needed to modify
it it would be like a piece of
software. You have Windows
10, Windows 11, and
so on right? Now that diagnostic system
came into being because
psychiatrists had a very hard time
agreeing with one another about what
was wrong with somebody, and that
became embarrassingly clear in
-- first in the professional
literature which outsiders
didn't read and then via a
very famous study that's a
scientific fraud by David
Rosenhan called On Being Sane
in Insane Places where he
claimed to have sent in pseudo
patients to the hospital
and they all were diagnosed as schizo.
All but one of them diagnosed as
schizophrenic the other as somebody
with bipolar disorder and they
were fake patients. So
almost in a panic after
that study appeared in Science and because
there was an abundant
professional literature from the
1960s showing the same thing that
diagnosis was a very erratic process.
The DSM-III task force led by Robert
Spitzer who was then at Columbia
was explicitly set up to try
to create a sort of tick the
boxes approach to deciding which box a
patient belonged in. Were you
schizophrenic? Were you this type of
schizophrenic or that type
of schizophrenic? Were you
manic depressive or bipolar? Did you
have various forms of depression?
And to construct those boxes what they
relied upon was a list of symptoms and if
you had more than a certain
number If you had more than
six of ten Six or ten or more
symptoms of a certain sort
you could be diagnosed with major
depression for example. So that
system came into being.
It was partially embedded
because it appealed to drug
companies who were developing
drugs to treat these various disorders.
It appealed to insurance companies 'cause
it gave them a stable base to look at.
It appealed to, as diagnosis always does
to patients and their families who are
scrambling to deal with these enormous
upsets in the mental life of either
themselves or a family member.
So provided some sense of
certainty around diagnosis.
But that was always based simply on
symptoms in the way an eighteenth
century doctor might
diagnose dropsy or diagnose,
Some other kind of disor---
Fever for example well
fever and other diseases they
talked about in the eighteenth
century are really a constellation of
very different things under one label.
And I think that's what is
turning out to be true of the
DSM labels. But that approach
was really all that psychiatry
could come up with if it
wanted to make sure whether you
were in Walla Walla or New York or
San Francisco or Atlanta you
reached the same conclusion faced
by the same patient. That you had
a reliable diagnostic system.
That didn't mean necessarily it was
a valid diagnostic system if you
understand the distinction
between validity and
reliability. Reliability means
you and I faced with the
same sets of facts reach
the same conclusion but
that conclusion may or may not reflect the
underlying reality of things
right? So you had this
diagnostic system and
it went through various
iterations each time it went
through an iteration the number
of possible psychiatric disorders you
could get grew and grew and grew and it
became difficult to believe in
some of those categories shall
we say. That they were
really illnesses rather
th-than some sorta social
construct. But beyond that um,
psychiatrists wanted to be more
like other medical doctors to root
their diagnoses in an
understanding of the underlying
pathology of the disorder.
What was it that caused
people to become
schizophrenic? The sense was
if we could grasp that we'd have a
better handle on how to attack it How
To treat it. And when uh, DSM-5 was mooted
the fifth edition in the early 2000s
NIMH then under the leadership
of Steven Hyman who's at
Harvard now and succeeded by Thomas Insel
who ruled NIMH for about
thirteen years. The
two of them had pushed
psychiatry and psychiatric
research in a very particular direction.
On the one hand, towards understanding
the genetics of mental illness,
and on the other, to looking at what the
new discipline of neuroscience could
contribute to understanding things.
Both of them were heavily invested
in the idea that mental
illness was brain disease.
And if it was brain disease, then
the question was what was making the
mechanism here go awry? What was
causing people's emotions or
their cognitive skills or
their sense of the world
to become so disordered?
And they invested a lot of money in
that approach. When Insel stepped
down, he gave an interview
actually to somebody at MIT
and he's repeated it since in a
book he wrote about his experiences
where he said, "Well, you know,
as I look back on my 13 years,
I funded an enormous amount of scientific...
really cool scientific research.
I funded geneticists and I
funded neuroscientists and
we-- they did a lot of
really interesting science."
And after spending 20 billion
dollars, the lot of the
mentally ill has improved
not one bit right?"
Which was a pretty devastating
statement, I thought.
- And NIMH is National
Institute of Mental Health.
- National Institute of Mental Health,
yes. I shouldn't resort to jargon.
But the National Institute of Mental
Health had been founded in the late
1940s with the goal of improving, doing
basic research training people in the field
advancing the care of the mentally
ill and producing obviously
cures and advances. Uh, and
its mission has varied widely
over the years since but starting in the
in the-- in the 1990s—the period
when the first George Bush
declared the decade of the brain—uh, NIMH
increasingly focused on the idea
that mental illness was purely a
brain disease and there's something
to that and there's also some
mistake in thinking about it that way.
- This is, by the way, as we will
talk about this distinction
between seeing mental health,
the maladies of the human mind,
as a problem of the brain, like
neurobiology, neuroscience, versus
the problem of the mind, which is more in
the cognitive, psychotherapy, these more,
less amenable to scientific
rigor. So I think what's
appealing about studying the brain and
neurobiology, neurosciences, there's
data. Yes. It's more
rigorous. You can do science.
- It’s the kind of thing that really
appealed to medical school deans because
once NIH and the drug companies
too were funding basic research on
neurobiology and basic research on
genetics, the money flooded in. Um, and
psychiatry, which had been something of
an orphan, became much more popular,
- and we should say that this is something you
write a lot about. There are all these factors to
consider. So there's cultural elements,
political, public policy elements. Then at
a certain point, drug companies,
insurance companies come in, of course.
all human beings around somebody who's
suffering with a mental health issue, so family
factors, that's connected, cultural stuff.
- it's a very complicated area and
oversimplification is a real problem I think.
Uh, and I think even that dichotomy
you just drew between, um, the
brain and the social or psychological,
some mix of those things,
I think in some ways that's a category mistake,
that's a mistaken way of looking at the
world, because the brain you have
today, you're not born with. Human
brains are remarkably plastic things.
They develop in response to the
environment. Social, psychological
are embedded in our brains.
Rigid separation, saying one or the
other—no. Abundant evidence from
epidemiology that social factors play an
important role in the development of illness.
- Nevertheless, history of psychotherapy,
for example, subfields...
human mind is complicated, all
these factors. To say anything
helpful, you have to simplify. Freud famously
simplified a lot towards a particular view of the human
mind. That simplification, actually,
we'll talk about if it's correct
in a deeper sense, was productive.
- Yes. In fact, whenever you're trying to
deal with a very complicated set of issues,
you have to simplify. You
have to make heuristic
decisions about what you're going
to neglect and what you're gonna
emphasize. But what I'm trying to say, well,
you asked me about the crisis in psychiatry,
and the simplest way for me to
encapsulate the issue and the
problem as I see it that's arisen—one
of the problems—is a quote by Leon
Eisenberg, who had a very long
career at Harvard, and Eisenberg
said towards the end of his
career, he said, "When I entered
psychiatry, it was brainless psychiatry,
leaving it mindless psychiatry." Yeah,
sums up the way the field to
a large degree has moved.
In the process, insights are lost, though
in other ways, things are being gained. Um,
Freudians tended to neglect the
biological, to suggest the brain
as a biological organism was
not something we needed to
worry about. We worried at the level of a
psychological model of how our
minds work. And all too often,
not exclusively because some of
the psychiatrists I'm friends with
are very sophisticated men and women and
do grasp that you can't move in these
bipolar directions. You've got
to meet somewhere in the middle.
But that sort of got lost, I
think, in all the enthusiasm for
neuroscience. I mean, when
antipsychotic drugs were discovered
in the early 1950s, we had no clue of
how they worked. And one of the things
that they helped us spawn as
people began to say, "Well,
why did these drugs
work? What did they do?"
Was to begin to understand that
the brain wasn't just a set of
electrical signals, as had been
thought in the first half of the 20th
century and before. But
rather there was this very
interesting chemical soup running
around in our brains with
neurotransmitters that help
the brain work the way it did
and perhaps explained why it went awry.
So it was one of the many factors
that gave rise to neuroscience. The
first neuroscience conventions were
in the 1970s, and they attracted a
few hundred people. Now
it's tens of thousands of
neuroscientists. It's
a huge enterprise. So
diagnosis has come under
threat. The categories that
we have all become familiar
with, that we're told are real
diseases like bipolar disorder,
schizophrenia, major depression,
are beginning to falter,
and we're beginning to
worry about whether
those diagnoses are real
ways of thinking about the world
and may in fact mislead us.
Because if we think there's something
called schizophrenia or the
schizophrenias, as the inventor
of that term put it, if we think
there's something like that and
we try to research where it
comes from, but that's not really what's
going on, obviously we're probably
gonna not make the progress we
could be making if we had a better
diagnostic system. And that's what
DSM-V thought it was gonna
be able to do and discovered
it couldn't. So it stayed basically
with the symptomatic approach.
- If we can just really brief -
I would love to talk a little bit more
about the DSM, but just to give a history
here, looking it up on Perplexity, DSM
One in 1952 was a 32 page pamphlet-
with 106 diagnoses heavily influenced
by psychodynamic concepts-
and etiology using broad, often
vague categories like reactions.
DSM Two in 1968 expanded to 185
diagnoses still psychodynamically
flavored and reliability poor,
but added more attention
to childhood disorders and later
removed homosexuality as a disorder in
1974 printing. Then to
the revolution, as you
mentioned, the DSM Three in
1980 introduced explicit
symptom-based diagnostic criteria, a multi
axial assessment system, and an officially
atheoretical stance about causes aiming to
improve reliability and research utility.
And then DSM Three R in
1987 revised criterion
expanded to around two 97 diagnoses.
DSM Four in '94 and DSM Four TR in
2000 focused on literature
driven empirical revisions,-
added and deleted some disorders
increased coordination with
ICD 10 and goes on. And then
finally in 2013 DSM Five came
out which eliminated the multiaxial system
integrated most information
into a single nonaxial
diagnostic list than separate notations
for psychological and medical
factors. It reorganized chapters e.g.
Neurodevelopmental, obsessive-compulsive
related, trauma and
stress related disorders introduce
new and refined entities and so
on. But big picture trajectory conceptually
the DSM moved from cause focused and
psychoanalytical to symptom-based,
theoretical, and reliability driven
over time. There has been growth in the
number of granularity of categories
closer alignment with
ICD ongoing controversy
over medicalization, validity,
and the balance between
categorical and dimensional
approaches. Yes. It
feels like that description doesn't
necessarily fully get to the
core of why the DSM five doesn't quite
get the full scope of the problem
- You invest a ton of money. You invest-
...$20 billion-- More than $20
billion in a particular approach.
And at the time you're constructing
this, you say, "Finally,
because of all the work that's
being done in genetics, we now have
decoded the human genome.
We have PCR so we can chop it up and we
can look at bits of it. We have a lot more
understanding of the role of
neurotransmission in the brain.
Surely we're going to be able
to recast our diagnostic system
based on underlying pathology
so that we won't be
worrying about symptoms anymore.
We'll be looking at the actual
underlying pathological
changes that have taken place.
But in the event, it turned out
they couldn't do that. By about
2008, they had thrown up their
hands and said, "No, we're going
to have to continue to refine,
rely upon the same basic approach
that we developed in 1980." And
when that document came out, and there'd
been a lot of criticism, some of it from
Robert Spitzer, who had been largely in
control of DSM-III and DSM-III-R, and then
his successor Allen
Frances, who'd run DSM-IV,
they both were fiercely critical about
what was going on and said it was
being done in the dark and it was done
in secrecy and it wasn't scientific.
And when it was about to come out,
Thomas Insel and Steven Hyman,
the two then existing and the
preceding director of the National
Institute of Mental Health, denounced the
document as unscientific and useless.
So if you're talking about a crisis,
that's a crisis for the field. If its
diagnostic system is being dissed
by leading figures like that,
What else was a problem? The
difficulties with the drug existing
therapies, particularly, had
become more and more manifest.
To make matters worse, partly because
Big Pharma had sometimes behaved,
shall we say, rather unethically sometimes
with these drugs, it had hidden things
that undercut their claims. It had
manufactured studies. It had manipulated data.
And it got caught out, and it paid
billions of dollars in damages
for some of the tricks it had got up to.
Not just in psychiatry—I
mean Vioxx, for example, the
painkiller, was another huge
scandal, and it was a $5 billion
settlement. But the drug companies had
suffered some reputational
damage. Beyond that, they didn't
have any real clues. Unfortunately,
neuroscience hadn't thrown up new
targets for different
forms of drug development
And they decided they could make more
money with spending their money on
research on other diseases,
not mental illness
A crisis was you were stuck with
a set of drugs that Steve Hyman
says, "Aren't really any
advance on the ones by
accident we found in the
fifties. Mm-hmm. And
there isn't new research unless
it's small startups going
on to develop new ones, so
you have an increasing sense
Your diagnostic process is falling apart, your
drug treatments' limitations are becoming
more manifest and, um, as well for people
with serious mental illness. Public
policy has screwed things up badly.
So if you, a person with serious
mental illness, you will
die on average fifteen to twenty-five
years before the rest of us. That
gap has been growing rather than
diminishing. So, that's not a good
thing. It's not something I want to
lay entirely at the door of psychiatry.
So don't get me wrong, I think a
lot of this is public policy that has really
abandoned treatment for the seriously
mentally ill. And you see it on
the streets of our cities. You
see the sidewalk psychotics.
You see people who are
cycling between brief periods of inpatient
care, uh, the gutter, or the flop
house and the jail. You so the three
largest centers of inpatient
psychiatric care, if you can call it
that in the United States
today are the Los Angeles
County Jail, Cook County Jail in
Chicago, and Rikers Island in New
York, that's shockingly, because by their very
nature, of course, prisons aren't equipped to
deal with serious mental illness
- Some dark ways to return
to the asylum era.
- Yeah, well, you know, the asylums had acquired a
very bad reputation, and I've written about some
of the reasons why that happened, but when
asylums were founded, it was a period of enormous
optimism that we were going to be able to cure these
people that we would rescue them from attics
and from jail cells, and through providing a
therapeutic environment, coaxing them to
work, creating a system where they learn to
control themselves, not necessarily to drive
their demons out, but to keep them under some
sort of wraps. The expectation was when the
asylums came along is that they'd not
only rescue people from horrendous
conditions in the prisons and
the jails, but they'd
actively cure them and
the earliest alienists, as they
called themselves then, thought that
they could cure 60, 70, 80 percent, maybe even
more of patients, as long as they came in early.
And really, asylums were
built out of that sense.
of optimism, that sense that we, you know,
that so much was environmental and so much was
Not exacerbating the condition by treating
people like animals or treating them, you know.
Beating them and in other ways horrifically
maltreating them, that would create, um, a sense of
Cure and really that underlay the
construction of the asylums and
Now having abandoned the asylums, which we did starting a
little bit in the 1950s but really the late 1960s onwards, uh.
That was because there was going to be
something miraculous called community care, but
Community care is a shell game without
a pee. It's like one o' those.
confidence tricks. There were no substitute
community facilities for dealing with
the really serious mentally ill.
- So now we're in this
truly, in, in this crisis-
... in this essentially
dark ages. And in part
I think our conversation, our journey
through the history of psychiatry-
... is an exploration of some
gigantic mistakes but also an
exploration of where lay some
hope for the future. So we'll
talk quite a bit about this. I
was wondering if you can also just lay out
what are the big categories of mental
illness that we're referring to. You've
already hinted at them, but
like levels of seriousness-
... and the categories of illness-
... like with psychosis
and depression and so on.
- So going back to the early 20th century
was when the German psychiatrist Emil
Kraepelin working with thousands
of records in German asylums
inductively developed a
distinction between two very
broad categories of mental illness.
One he called dementia
praecox or early dementia,
and the other he called manic depressive
illness which was a more remitting
illness that sometimes went away entirely,
other times went back and forth whereas
dementia praecox was a one way ticket down.
Now that label was transformed
by a Swiss psychiatrist Bleuler
into the term we use today
schizophrenia although
Bleuler talked about the
schizophrenias because he thought
under that broad label there were a
diverse group of things running around.
And I think that was an important
insight that tends to get lost
sometimes. This was
jamming together people
with very serious psychosis,
that is people who'd lost touch
with we liked-- what we like
to think of as reality,
whose emotional and cognitive
lives were in total turmoil,
Who were -- who lost
the ability to connect
with other human beings.
So their social skills
atrophied, their-- Well, this
is something contemporary
psychiatrists would refer to as the positive
and negative symptoms of schizophrenia.
- But underlying the definition
of schizophrenia here is a
detachment from reality. So you're hearing
voices- ... you're seeing visions.
- You're thinking people are plotting
against you. You think the
television is talking directly to you.
- And because of that it has these
consequences of how you're
connected to the rest of the world and what your
emotional life is like, all that kind of stuff.
- Yes. Your emotional life flattens
out. Your language capacity
deteriorates. Your ability
to relate to other people
either vanishes or becomes
caught up in the web of
delusions where you think
people around you are plotting
against you or doing
terrible things to you.
- And is that a different world than
the world of bipolar and the world of
depression?
- Yes. The Greeks recognized and
the Romans, ancient Greece and
ancient Rome recognized different
forms of insanity as they called it.
So melancholia
would have been the term the Greeks
and the Romans would have used and it
survived and was very much around.
And I think that is a form of
depression. What's happened now is major
depression has become a catchall category.
So it embraces both what we might think
of as milder forms of emotional distress
along with what melancholia
referred to which was really
a kind of depression that had
psychotic features. This loss of
contact as it were with everyday reality.
- Something you would talk about maybe like
a clinical depression. And by the way, we
should mention that this field in the
21st century is like a minefield.
- Yes, very much so. So here's a very strange
bit of historical record. The other
distinction and the distinction
we're grappling with so we
have people who are-- whose
depression is of such a scale they're
threatening to do away with
themselves. They've retreated
into complete almost immobility. They're
overwhelmed by senses
of sadness and loss and
they're-- If they're religious then
they're damned to hell and all those
kinds of things. So we have this psychosis
that we've been talking about.
We have something also that the
ancients recognize: dementia;
the loss really the loss
of our mind as it were.
But then we also have
other kinds of disturbance of our
mental faculties that generally
we think of as more minor but I
don't want to make light of them
because often people suffer
from these things genuinely
suffer pretty badly. But
those things-- we in
the 20th and 21st centuries
tend to talk about as neuroses
neurotic diseases, psychotic diseases.
In the 19th century neurosis was a
term that meant things rooted
in the brain as you can
see from the root of the word
and psychosis was stuff that
came from the mind, the psyche.
And yet sometime in the late 19th
century those things crossed over
and so when we talk in the present we do
tend to distinguish between the core,
really the most severe
forms of mental disorder,
...which would include things
like Alzheimer's disease
and other forms of dementia, would include
very serious depression,
would include bipolar
disorder where people oscillate
either have extreme mania so they're
they're not getting any sleep. They're
talking at an extraordinary rate
Their behavior is very hard to
tolerate, and they're exhausting
themselves, and they may even die from
exhaustion if it's not controlled.
And very often that
alternates with periods of
depression. So that was a category
that was captured initially as,
Manic depressive illness
and later on evolved into
bipolar disorder and then
separating out depression
and major depression separately.
But then there are a whole bunch of
other things like, for example, phobias.
People can't go outside because
they find it too frightening.
Milder phobias: "I can't get in an
airplane because it's gonna crash,"
"I can't go to school because it's
overwhelming for me." So school phobia
emerges as a diagnosis. A disorder that
at first attracted Freud, hysteria.
- And now we should say you
wrote a book on hysteria.
- Oh, I did indeed, yes.
- You mentioned ... I mean, hysteria,
every classification we're
talking about has been
used and abused by every
layer of society including institutions-
- Yes
- ...including just culturally the word
hysteria applied to different races
disproportionately, to different, um-
- Genders particularly, yes, yes
- ...genders disproportionate-
So we're in this crisis of trying to
figure out what to do with this super
complicated human mind-
- Yes
- ...and everybody is dogmatically creating
narratives that hold, take hold, and
in so doing can lead to some abuses-
- Yes, they do. Yes, they do
- ...as you document.
- If you look back at the asylum era
born in this period of intense
optimism, and then the claims
to be able to cure these vast
numbers of patients were overblown.
Uh, I do believe the early asylums
actually did good work and that some
patients did very well and recovered as a
result of their stays. But what happened,
they weren't discharging 80% of their
patients. They were discharging
35 or 40% of their patients, and what
that meant is every year left behind
were a batch of chronic patients, and then
the next year you repeated it. And over
time, what that means is the ratio of new
patients to chronic patients
gets worse and worse.
And more and more the image of
the asylum is defined by the
chronic patient who hasn't
recovered and maybe spends years or
decades there and only leaves in a pine
box. So the image of the asylum declined
drastically. As they became
more and more overcrowded,
conditions in them deteriorated.
Patients were often
abused. Psychiatrists didn't know
what to do with them, and they
faced a problem in the late 19th century.
You'd promised 70% or 80% cures,
but we're not seeing that. In fact, when
we calculate cures and the numbers of
people in the asylum, it's
more like 10% or 12%. That's
the way you could play with statistics
'cause that's all the old patients
mixed with the new. But still, it looks
very bad. How do you explain this doctor?
You've promised us one thing, and you
delivered something quite different. The
answer came in a way of
blaming the victim, in a way
of saying, "Well, you know,
what we didn't understand
was that mental illness is
a fundamentally biological
condition. These people are evolutionary
throwbacks." Evolution was
generally thought of as a
progressive onwards and upwards,
but these people had fallen back
into a lesser form of
existence. They'd lost their essential
humanity because their brains were defective.
So what emerged then was the idea
of degeneration, the idea that
these patients were degenerates.
They were people with an inferior
biology. You couldn't release them because
they breed like rabbits. They didn't
have any self-control because
of their diminished humanity.
- This is the narrative.
- This is the narrative. And
so what it did was provide a
justification for locking up people
in asylums that wasn't therapeutic
at all. It was just keeping
them out of the way.
- And then it led to the
justification of sterilization-
- Exactly.
- ...based on the same argument.
- So maybe we can release them if
we make sure they can't breed.
- This is the beginning of the darkness.
- It is the beginning of the
darkness. My own state was
one of the pioneers in
this process, and it
continued to sterilize mental
patients up until about 1960.
- By the 1960s, over 60,000 sterilizations
have been performed in the US with
California performing a
disproportionately high number.
- That's correct. But even more serious
consequences could flow
from these set of issues.
When you start talking, one British
psychiatrist said that if his patients that
were coming into the
asylum had been puppies,
we'd have tied them up in a sack because
they were some horrible mongrel, not
a purebred dog, tied them up in a sack with
some lead weights, and thrown them in a
pond and drowned them.
- Man.
- That kind of language is
very, very dangerous.
And what happened,
California's law surrounding
sterilization was advocated
for in the West. By that I
mean North America and
Britain and much of Europe.
There were enough checks and balances
in a democratic system that even
though there were enthusiasts,
the eugenicists who said,
"Best get rid of these
people, put them to death,"
that never really, that never
really acquired mass support.
But what happened in Germany
once Nazi-- the Nazis came to
power is they seized on these
notions and that the idea
that the mentally ill were, as
they put it, useless eaters,
people consuming resources but never
gonna get better, just a burden on
the state. Their lives weren't worth
living because after all, they had this
serious mental illness. So first you
sterilize, and then you go, "But
we're still supporting all these
people." And so Hitler starts
something called the T4 program
after the street name of the house where
this was concocted, Tiergartenstraße 4.
And the mentally ill were the first
people to suffer from the Final Solution.
It was in the mass killing of the mentally
ill, which may have been as many as a
quarter million people, that the technology
of the gas chamber was developed,
and the technology of disguising the
gas chamber as showers was developed.
And so patients were taken away
to a number of psychiatric
centers and systematically
put to death, and they had the
crematoriums and the black
smoke, and local people talked about
the buses that were bringing them in as
killing crates. So they were
aware of what was going on.
- Were they influenced by the narratives
that were born in the United States?
- Yes, absolutely. They-
- About this kind of-
- About that sort of thing, and
lacking the check, the checks and
balances that at least until
recently this country had, um,
it was relatively easy for Hitler
to do that. And particularly
with the war looming, the idea
that we're gonna support all
these useless people, let's kill
them. And German psychiatry for the most
part collaborated with that process.
- I wonder how many people throughout that
whole journey in the psychiatry profession
sort of were brave enough to
speak up like, "Hey, maybe the
sack of puppies kinda language-"
- Oh, yes. Oh, yes.
- ... is a problem?"
- That's the really nasty direction
that that language could lead to.
And it was symptomatic of the kind of
stigma that tends to attach
itself to mental illness and this
sense of hopelessness. So but
if you're a healing profession,
if, if you enter psychiatry thinking,
"I'm gonna do this to help people, to
cure people, to make their lives better,"
to just become a glorified boarding
housekeeper keeping them under lock and key
or in the alternative to collaborate
in this, in the sorts of
awfulness that the Nazis
perpetrated, that's
something from which decent human beings
tend to recoil and decent
psychiatrists tended to recoil. And so
still thinking as they did
by the end of the 19th
century that mental illness was
predominantly a biological problem,
some of them began to say, "Well,
maybe biology as well as being the
problem could provide the
solution. Maybe we should look for
ways to intervene in the biological systems
of these people and make them better."
The same logic that applies
I would say in the present-
... for, for many working in the field.
- But in a cruder form.
- But in a very different form, exactly.
- Yeah. If, if we can just speak
about the Nazis a bit more, you
highlight that America financially
supported the German psychiatric
researchers with deep Nazi
ties like Ernst Rudin who was
the key architect of Hitler's mass
sterilization and extermination
laws. So it seems like the Nazis borrowed
the American narratives of the
psychiatrist that these are lesser
biological beings and then this financial
support and the ties continued.
- Yeah. So one of the organizations that
recognized that mental illness was an acute
social problem, very costly to the state
inflicting all kinds of suffering on
people was The Rockefeller Foundation.
What we don't realize today is that the
involvement of the federal
government in medical research
and indeed scientific
research is a World War II
and post-war development partly
the Cold War and Sputnik and
all of that. But that's when big
science and big medicine got funded-
... in extravagant ways. Before the war,
science was an orphan. It didn't get
money from the government much and
medicine even more so. So to the extent
medical training was reformed, that was the
product of investment by The Rockefeller
Foundation enormously wealthy
by the standards of the
time. And come about 1930,
The Rockefeller Foundation
decided it needed
to concentrate its resources and pick
priorities for the money it was investing.
And it may seem a rather
strange thing within the
whole range of medical
areas that it could choose,
it chose psychiatry as the one that
it was going to invest in. And
I think it did so in part for
precisely because scientific research
in psychiatry was so backward,
partly because it was such
a pressing public problem.
And partly, and this was less
public but nonetheless I
think played an important role,
several of the trustees of The
Rockefeller Foundation had
direct experience of mental
illness in their families.
Wives who'd been
institutionalized as
schizophrenic. In one case, a
wife who murdered the
children and killed herself
leaving her husband as
a major actor in The
Rockefeller Foundation bereft
and of course inclined
then to support research in this area. And
Rockefeller spread its money very widely,
Precisely 'cause it didn't
know where to spend most of
its money. So it did some support of
Psychotherapeutics. It
supported a number of the then
extant therapeutic experiments going on,
and it supported work in genetics.
And one of the geneticists it
supported, Ernst Rüdin in
Germany, who was the leading
German researcher in genetics
and mental disorder.
And Rüdin, because he's absorbed
the lessons from California
about sterilization, became a very
enthusiastic proponent of that,
and then a supporter of
murdering mental patients.
- And we should say, I mean, we'll probably
talk about the complicated nature of science-
...that it sometimes can be
captured by certain ideologies and-
...in so doing do a lot of
damage to humanity. But
ultimately, the beacon of hope for
the future of humanity lays in the
scientific method, as flawed as it is.
So everything we're talking about,
we get to see how you F up-
In a major dark disturbing ways
throughout the 20th century-
...on the-- in the psychiatric
profession. But that
should be instructive lessons
of how we proceed forward to do
better and better and better.
- We can discuss a series of therapeutic
experiments on people who were shut up in a
double sense. They were locked away,
and their voices were not heeded
because it was the product of their
madness. And so what we see in
the first five decades really of the 20th
century is people with a
variety of motivations
including the desire to improve
the lot of the mentally ill
engaging in uncontrolled experiments
that had terrible results.
And the science behind it
was shaky but nonetheless
it existed. It wasn't just
plucked out of the sky.
And yes, it eventually those things
break down. I mean, the clearest case
of that because it's the most
extreme of these at least in the
public imagination is lobotomy. The
idea that you are going to solve
psychotic breakdowns in people
by excising part of their brain
initially by drilling holes in
the skull and injecting alcohol
or using what looks like a butter
knife to break connections
between the brain. And then
later when that process
seems to be too slow, the
Henry Ford of lobotomy--
his daughter said Walter Freeman aspired
to be the Henry Ford of lobotomy, the
one who could mechanize the
production of it and get it done
fast. He invented the ice
pick lobotomy where you
used an ice pick in the orbit of the eye
having rendered somebody unconscious
after two or three electric shocks
and you banged it through the
bone and wiggled it about and
severed -- I mean, it's
just hard to even describe.
- So this is from the 1930s to the 1970s?
- Yes. Freeman starts his work in 1936
borrowing from the work of the
preceding year of Portuguese
neurologist named Egas Moniz.
And Moniz wins the Nobel
Prize in medicine in 1949 for lobotomy.
So it's important to see
that. That was 14 years
of experience and yet that
won a Nobel Prize. I'm
sure that's one they'd like to retract.
- So he popularized Walter
Freeman, the ice pick.
- And his particular specialty after
the war became this ice pick
lobotomy because there were
over half million patients in
America's mental hospitals. Freeman
was convinced this operation was
a cure all. And so he traveled
around in a camper truck
which he called the Lobotomobile
and he would descend in the
summer on state hospitals and he would teach
them how to do this ice pick lobotomy.
- This is by the way an image of the tool.
- Yes, those are the tools he used. Originally,
he used an actual ice pick and then
he developed this-
- This is what he developed. This is
the state-of-the-art technology.
- This is the state of the art
with a hammer or a mallet.
- Oh no!
- Yes, I'm sorry. It's very
distressing. I, I don't know-
- You having to write
about this by the way--
- Well, it's really-
- Is a lot
- ...very, very, very, very
difficult. I came across, for
example, picture of a woman, naked woman
being dragged away by attendants
to be lobotomized and she's
resisting with all her might and to
no avail. You have a picture there of
Walter Freeman lobotomizing a
patient in Washington State.
Freeman was ambidextrous and when he taught
neurology, he would draw simultaneously
with his left and right hand
and he could do it perfectly.
When he was performing lobotomy, when
his right hand got tired, he switched to
his left hand and he sometimes would do
20 or 30 lobotomies in an afternoon.
And he boasted, he said, "You
know I could teach any damn
fool to perform a lobotomy in twenty
minutes even a psychiatrist."
Because Freeman was a neurologist and he
had a lot of contempt for psychiatrists. So
So this was a very ugly episode.
How did it die away? It really took
generational change. Some of these
lobotomists continued to operate into the
sixties even to the early seventies,
but the younger generation
who became acquainted
with the really worst failures of that
regime; the people on the back wards
who were incontinent, who were
basically zombies had
lost all mental power.
They rebelled against
this and by then they had
a different treatment in the
form of antipsychotic drugs-
... which looked much more like
what regular medicine was doing,
And didn't have these
horrible overtones. And of
course in the popular mind I think
the, probably the most famous,
instance of telling the public about
some of these interventions was the
film of Ken Kesey's novel One
Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest
where you see Jack Nicholson giving
I think the performance of a
lifetime who is given ECT,
electroconvulsive therapy,
at--in a very dramatic rendition
of what that was not, not really
what was going on by, by the 1970s
with ECT but nonetheless certainly
what had been going on back in the
past. And then finally when
ECT doesn't smash him to bits
they lobotomize him and, and the
film ends obviously with him being
smothered to death 'cause Chief can't bear
to see him in, in the state that he's in.
So that fixed in the public mind
some of the images of these things.
It is one of the things that gave
Electroconvulsive therapy such a bad name.
- So we will actually not to
fast forward too quickly,-
-... let's talk about uh, the full journey
of everything we've been talking about. So we
mentioned the asylum era that began in the
mid nineteenth century going into twentieth
and we talked about the narratives-
- And we talked about sterilization
- Sterilization. And let's look at the
insulin shock therapy of uh, nineteen
thirty three to the nineteen sixties
where you were putting patients
in deep hypoglycemic comas
using large doses of insulin.
- Yeah. So as I mentioned
for psychiatrists who
went into the field and were
ambitious but who also wanted to
think of themselves as therapeutic agents-
....uh, to just sit there
passively and contain the patients
was very unattractive. And so they
looked around for ways in which perhaps
biological interventions could be used
to ameliorate this condition that they
still saw in largely biological terms.
Now in some ways one of the crucial
early ways in which this thinking went
and which affected a large
number of patients was this:
one of the few diagnostic triumphs of
psychiatry in the early nineteenth
century as the profession began to emerge
Was that it began to distinguish a
group of patients who were deemed
to be suffering from something called
general paralysis of the insane.
That encapsulates two things about
what was going on. First of all,
paralysis; the gradual
loss of motor control,
ability to walk, ability to
swallow, ability to, to talk.
So those are primarily what we'd
think of these days as neurological
issues. But those were
accompanied by bizarre
psychiatric symptomatology. These
were people who thought they were
Napoleon or Jesus Christ or the
richest and sexiest man in the world-
...or Mary the mother of
God. They were primarily men
but there were also female victims.
At the turn of the twentieth
century as many as twenty
five percent of the people
being admitted to asylums
were suffering from General Paralysis
of the Insane or GPI for short.
There have been a lot of suspicions
about this being connected somehow to
sex and to moral dissolution and so forth
but what evolved in the early
twentieth century was the
discovery of the actual origins of this
disorder. So I've said psychiatry
has been looking for the
underlying pathology
that lies behind mental
diseases. This was one that
at Rockefeller Institute
they discovered that the organism that causes
syphilis was residing in the brains of
the people who were suffering
from GPI. This was in
fact tertiary stage of
syphilis. Syphilis is a
still a real public health problem. It
was like AIDS in the late nineteenth
century. It was everywhere.
And when you first contract syphilis
in the primary phase you have pain
but then it goes underground
and you think it's gone
and it lurks the way chicken
pox virus lurks and can
surface years later right? It lurks, it lurks
and it's insidiously damaging sometimes
it attacks the heart and people drop dead
of a heart attack in their forties ohh
he died of a-- You know it's natural heart
attack but in fact it was the syphilis
Or it attacks the central nervous
system the spinal column in the brain
and then you get the paralysis -
Mm-hmm ...and then you get also the
psychiatric symptomatology. So when that
was discovered that sort of suggested
that mental illness might
have an infectious origin.
Tertiary syphilis GPI went on to win for
somebody who developed a treatment
for it a Nobel Prize one of only
two awarded for psychiatric
innovations. One was a lobotomy
the other was giving people
malaria to cure their syphilis.
- In case people didn't hear
that- Giving people malaria-
.. In order to cure syphilis
- So there was an Austrian doctor, Wagner
Jauregg, who had long thought that
fever could be used to cure
mental illness. And he tried rat
bite fever. He tried giving people
typhoid vaccine that creates a
fever to no avail. And towards
the end of World War I,
the Italians were fighting in
World War I on the side of the
British and the Americans and the French.
They captured an Italian
soldier who had malaria.
Malaria was endemic in
those years in Italy.
And they brought him to him, and he
extracted the malarial blood and
injected it into a series
of patients with GPI, with
general paralysis of the insane,
and claimed it cured them.
We know from later on
when he fessed up that
those claims were wildly
exaggerated, but they were widely
accepted, and malarial treatment
spread to Britain, it spread to Germany,
it spread to the United States.
Sometimes it was vials of malarial
blood, but very often mental
hospitals had actual colonies
of malarial mosquitoes.
So imagine you're a mental patient, and
you're put in a straitjacket, and you're put
in a room, and you can't move, and
mosquitoes are buzzing around,
and they bite you, and
then you develop malaria.
- And he got a Nobel Prize for this?
- Yes, in 1937, he got a Nobel
Prize. 'Cause this was a
condition that was invariably fatal.
And the claim was that somehow
the malarial fever worked.
Now, there are two possible
ways. Von Jauregg thought
it stimulated the
immune system to attack whatever
it was, was causing the insanity.
But the other possibility
was the following: When
you have the malarial parasite in a test
tube and you heat the test tube to about
105, 106 degrees, it dies. So the idea
potentially was you were sort of burning
the parasites out of the brain with
this agent. And because people
were pretty unsophisticated about
statistics and because the idea of a
controlled trial had not yet come to pass,
this treatment was used extensively
for a couple of decades. What
caused it to stop, and you talk
about the progress of science,
was the discovery of penicillin,
which was a real magic bullet.
So once you had penicillin, you
weren't gonna continue treating people
with malaria, so it died
away. But it was the first
such treatment, and here's the
other way this feeds into the
narrative of these desperate
remedies that develop in this
period between the
mid-'teens and, say, 1950.
The discovery of the syphilitic origins
of general paralysis of the insane
occurred at a time when
medicine had undergone a
undergone a profound
transformation. In the late 19th
century, the work of Louis Pasteur,
who was a chemist, not an MD,
and the work of Robert Koch
in Germany had uncovered
the origins of a variety of diseases and
suggested that bacteria were the reason why
people sickened. And that led, of
course, to a whole series of public
health triumphs, because initially it
didn't lead to antibiotics. But for a lot
of these diseases, even viral diseases
like rabies, you could develop a vaccine.
And the vaccines were
phenomenally effective. And so
that was one way in which the
new germ theory of disease
transformed medicine and tied it into the
laboratory and into science in a new way.
And the other was the adaptation
of Pasteur's theories
by a British surgeon named Lister,
who previously when pus developed
post-surgery, people had
thought that was a good sign.
Lister said, "No, I don't think
so. This is actually these
nasty germs causing this,
and so we're gonna do
antiseptic surgery." So
he sprayed carbolic acid
on the wounds to try to kill the microbes.
Most of his colleagues thought he
was nuts. Thought he was just-- This
is ridiculous, these microorganisms. You
couldn't even see them, you know? Well, you
could with a... But Lister prevailed.
And eventually we moved from
antiseptic surgery to aseptic
surgery, which is what we have now,
where you try to have a sterilized set of
instruments in a sterilized environment,
so you don't infect things, right?
- By the way, these are definitive
examples of progress in medicine.
- Absolutely.
- Penicillin--
- Yes.
- ...uh, you know, making sure
there's no germs in during surgery.
- Associated with wounds, yes.
- So these are all just refreshingly
clear examples of progress.
The reason I say it's refreshingly clear
that there's progress, there's not a
refreshingly clear progress in the history
of psychiatry. Maybe, maybe a few hints.
- Some bits, yes. There haven't been
the dramatic breakthroughs that
I think everybody in the field
would hope for. And
there's some debate about
how powerful what we have done is, and I
think it's reasonable to debate
that and to also acknowledge
that there is important progress, limited
as it is. Now you have 25% of the admits
to a mental hospital actually
suffering from an infectious
disease. Medicine in general has now
tied its fortunes to the laboratory.
The idea that disease is caused by
bacteria, we can't yet see viruses.
It is a very powerful one and that notion
that disease is caused by bacterial
infection acquires great momentum but it
hasn't touched psychiatry so medicine
now has interventions that work
And sometimes quite dramatically
um you know the first patient
given diphtheria vaccine--
Diphtheria causes a leather
like membrane to grow over your
throat and you die choking
to death And if you have a
child and you watch that child die
like that You will never be over it
So when you had something
that warded that off
That improved medicine's
image dramatically and
improved its financial prospects
dramatically particularly
as medical training became reformed
and more involved with science
So that hasn't applied to psychiatry until
syphilis comes along Now
we have the model that an
infectious agent can cause
people's minds to go amok
So The very person who
invents the basic distinction
between kinds of psychoses we still use
today schizophrenia and bipolar disorder
Emil Kraepelin begins to think "You
know there may be something infectious
about the mental illnesses
we're treating."
And one of the people he trains is a young
psychiatrist from the United States
named Henry Cotton Who's also
been trained by Adolf
Meyer who is the leading
American psychiatrist of the first
forty years of the twentieth century
And when he comes back from
Germany having spent a year there
Meyer secures him a position as
head of the New Jersey State Mental
Hospital at Trenton and Cotton
is an ambitious reforming man
He wants to bring psychiatry
back to medicine He also
wants to chuck out all the
old stuff He doesn't want
chains in his hospital He doesn't want
If he can help it straight jackets
So that goes away But nothing seems to
change fundamentally He still isn't
curing patients And then he
comes across this idea of
focal sepsis The idea that low grade
infections can lurk in the body
and what they do is release
toxins into the bloodstream
and the lymph And hey
imagine if those toxins get to
the brain What's it going to do?
It's gonna poison the brain and
the brain is then gonna act up
so We don't have antibiotics So
what are we gonna do about this
Well we can perhaps locate
the bacterial infection
and then we can Get rid of it We can engage
in what he calls surgical bacteriology
So the first obvious target here is teeth
Your teeth look close to your
brain They're often infected
That infection often goes untreated for
a time... So we pull a lot of teeth
Patients don't get better Mm Maybe
the theory's wrong No Um tonsils
well they're getting infected so we'll
remove them Still don't get better
Well they're swallowing the bacteria so
we remove stomachs and we move spleens
and we remove colons And we claim
to be curing eighty percent
of our patients And rich patients
come from all over America
to be treated with this novel treatment
- Crazy
- Cotton gives A series of lectures
at Princeton There were not
some lectures which are given by
Nobel Prize winners. There's a very
prestigious series.
Uh, it's published by Oxford University
Press and Princeton University Press.
The New York Times hails it as a
great breakthrough. And in reality,
45% of the people who get the
abdominal surgery die within a year.
- They're cutting out stomachs.
- Yep. He's cutting out stomachs. He
says--there's this passage in one of his papers
where he says, "Stomachs are like
cement mixers on a construction
site and could be dispensed
with." When you think, oh my God,
if you were released from
Trenton and you had no
teeth, people immediately knew you were an
ex-patient because the word had spread.
And this goes on for--starting
in 1916, Cotton drops dead of a
heart attack in 1933, but he's succeeded
by three people he's trained. They
drop the abdominal surgery. They
use colonic irrigation, but
but the teeth and the tonsils keep
being pulled. I interviewed the dentist
who had come to the hospital in
1916 and must have pulled several
hundred thousand teeth.
In nine-- and he retired in 1960,
which was when that finally stopped.
And he was convinced Cotton should have
won the Nobel Prize for this. Oh, well.
- Can you just give some
intuition, put ourselves in that
mind space? I mean,
presumably these are smart
human beings. Why were they
fraudulent in the reporting of how
effective it is? Why are all the
people that are participating,
both the doctors and general culture--
- It's extraordinary. So obviously,
many of the interventions I'm
talking about are very powerful
interventions conducted by people in white
coats and stethoscopes and scalpels.
- Powerful, by the way,
by the amount of impact
they have on the human body, not powerful
in terms of how effective they are.
- Yes, powerful as well in
terms of placebo effect.
Look, what I am going to do to
you, and yes, it's gonna hurt
and it's very intimate, but
it's going to make you better.
So that's always-- this is
a problem that persists in
contemporary psychiatry,
trying to figure out
how much of the improvement we're seeing
is the placebo effect and how-- how
much of it is the active effect of
whatever we're doing.
- But by the way, on that small tangent,
let's return to that perhaps often.
- Yes.
- I for one can tell you
that for me, for my mind,
the placebo effect even when you
tell me it's placebo will work.
- Yes!
- But now if you have
combined an actual gigantic
operation that is physically,
mentally, in every way life changing -
... everybody around you in lab
coats, all of society's telling
you this is going to be life changing.
I get it. That's like the most
pure kind of placebo effect.
- It's placebo effect that comes from both
the patient who wants to be better-
... and wants to believe this is
gonna make them, and from the person
conducting. And it's easy
to deceive yourself,
to see what you want to see. So
anyway, that was one episode. Um,
we talk about triumphs of medicine
so let me talk about one of
the real triumphs of 20th century medicine
which is interesting to refer
to because it wasn't a cure,
just like psychiatric drugs
aren't a cure for mental illness.
It was a symptomatic treatment
but it transformed lives
and that was discovery
of insulin in the 1920s.
Previously particularly
what we now call type
one or juvenile diabetes
was a death sentence.
You got it and whatever you
did, you tried various quack
remedies, you tried diet, you
tried all sorts of things. The
inevitable thing was it killed
you. And then came insulin.
Now insulin doesn't mean you're cured of
dia- your diabetes but what it means is
you can live a relatively normal
life and your lifespan is
greatly expanded. So by any measure you
have to say that's dramatic progress.
But insulin is something
our bodies produce we hope
unless we're really seriously
diabetic. Those of us with Type
Two diabetes, our bodies
resist insulin and we have
to resort to other ways
of trying to cope. But
if you get too much insulin,
it makes you unconscious
and that's how another one of these
desperate remedies came along.
A man named Sakel working
in a German clinic
for drug addicts they were using putting
people under mild comas
to help them through the
withdrawal symptoms once they got
over their addiction. So he was
familiar with that. And when
he moved to Austria, he
decided he'd try this as a
treatment for schizophrenia.
And so he put people into comas
sometimes comas that would
last hours days um they would be
revived by giving them glucose
usually intravenously sometimes not. Um
during the time they were in
comas they often seized had
seizures. He saw that
as a therapeutic sign.
And he claimed that this
Insulin Coma Treatment
cured eighty percent of his -- eighty
percent tends to come up again and again
in these treatments as a sort
of percentage that you cure.
And he was invited to New York
and demonstrated this at the
Harlem Valley Mental Hospital.
It spread. This is in the
thirties? This was starting in
nineteen thirty-three. The visit to
America was I believe nineteen thirty-
six and Sakel ended up
settling here. He had a very
lucrative private practice in
New York and when he died he
left his partner I think an estate
of about two million dollars which
in the early sixties was
a very substantial amount
of money that he'd earned
from practice, right? So
insulin coma therapy was
widely adopted. What kept it
from being a large scale thing
was it required an enormous
amount of nursing and medical
attention 'cause people were literally
hovering on the brink of life and
death. They could go into a permanent
coma, they could just die. Um, so they had
vital signs had to be monitored.
They had to be brought around very
quickly if need be. And there's some
evidence that the treatment killed
brain cells. And when Sakel was told
that, he said, "Yes, that's probably
true. They're killing the schizophrenic
brain cells." That's just
nonsense, of course. That's
just nonsense, but that's
his rationale. Insulin comas
weren't subjected to a
randomized controlled
trial until the nineteen
fifties. And when they were
subjected to a controlled
trial, they failed it, and so it died out.
And that's, I guess, scientific
progress again in a way, but
took a long time. One of the people who
received insulin coma therapy—have you seen
the film A Beautiful Mind? Mm-hmm, he did.
Receive insulin coma therapy. Ironically, actually at Trenton
State Hospital where Cotton had been, so John Nash received
John Nash got insulin comas, and
they were going to lobotomize him,
and they didn't, but he was at
risk of that. We should say
that this treatment, patients would thrash, moan, and convulse before falling into a coma. The treatment required a course of up to sixty comas. It turned out
to have a mortality rate of one to five percent and caused significant brain damage and obesity. Yeah, yet was hailed as a miracle cure for schizophrenia.
Yes, that's right. Performed
on John Nash, one of the great
- minds of the 20th century.
- Yes, and Nash clearly
did become delusional,
but that was one of the
treatments he was subjected to,
and well represented, actually,
in the film of A Beautiful Mind.
So I mentioned seizures. Also in
Austria-Hungary in this period,
another psychiatrist decided
that you couldn't be both
schizophrenic and epileptic. That there
was somehow an antagonism between the two.
So if you had epilepsy, you didn't
have schizophrenia. If you had
schizophrenia, you couldn't have epilepsy.
Uhh... I should say at the outset, that's
not true, but that's what he believed.
So then, the logical next step
was, "Well, if we could create
an artificial epileptic seizure, maybe
we would drive out the schizophrenia."
So, what to do? He first tries injecting
camphor, a natural substance. Natural
substances aren't necessarily
benign substances. That
caused abscesses, and it
wasn't very effective. He sought
an alternative, and he settled
on something that was,
um, called Cardiazol
or Metrazol, depended which side
of the Atlantic you were on.
And injecting that into a
patient usually caused a
seizure, a big seizure like
a grand mal seizure, where
your body arcs back, your
legs contract dramatically.
- You can fracture spines
and hips and bones.
- And you ended up, yes, with
fractures of vertebrae, fractures
of the hip socket. Because
when muscles in the
thigh contract that badly,
what happens? The thigh bone
is driven into the socket at
such a rate that it fractures,
right? So these were among the
complications that Metrazol
produced. More than that,
he himself conceded
that between the injection
and the seizure, the
patient felt as though he were on--
or she was on the brink of death.
Now imagine, pretend you're a mental patient.
You're brought in in a straitjacket, a
man in a white coat with a big
hypodermic injects something into you,
You feel as though you're gonna die.
And maybe that lingers for two,
three, ten minutes, and then
you seize, with those
possible fractures following.
- Violent seizures.
- It's violent and hard to witness
and is very unpredictable.
So it's used, but people are
not very happy, and that's
how we get electroconvulsive therapy,
electroshock, as it's first called. Two Italian
psychiatrists, Cerletti and Bini,
experiment with electricity, and they
first experiment on dogs.
And they make a mistake initially. They
have an electrode on the head, an electrode
on the anus. The electric current passes
through the body, it stops the heart, the
dogs die.
So that seems a dead end. And then somebody
says to them, "You know, you should go to
the Rome slaughterhouse and see the pigs
being slaughtered, 'cause you'll learn
something very interesting." So they
go, and the pigs are dangling by their
hind legs, and as they come by,
two electrodes cross their head.
Electroshock, they convulse,
they're unconscious, their
throats are slit and pork arrives. So, um,
they try that on dogs, and current passing
through the brain, it turns
out, doesn't kill them.
So they decide to try it out.
They pick up a transient
homeless person at the Rome train
station and they bring him in.
And they try it, and at first
they don't use enough current.
And nothing very much happens.
And they're very white-
faced, they're quite worried off in the corner.
We have descriptions of this, and they're
talking, "What should we do?" "Well,
we'll up the current." And the patient
hears that and says, "No, another one, that's
deadly." They do it anyway, and he convulses.
Another grand mal seizure, with the
same problems of spinal fractures
and hip fractures and so on. Not
universally, obviously, but often enough.
And he stops breathing.
You can imagine the scene.
And then he spontaneously starts breathing
again, and when he comes around,
he's in contact with reality.
They got this miracle cure,
and it's very easy to administer, cheap,
doesn't involve injecting things into
people's bodies. So that quickly spreads
across the Atlantic and
other parts of Europe.
And ECT becomes a very
widely used intervention.
Couple of things to say about this.
It turns out it's not very
useful for schizophrenia.
Remember the connection
between seizures and
seizure and schizophrenia
that was originally posited
posited, but it seems to
work in cases of, um,
depression, suicidal
depression particularly.
- Fast forwarding to the modern day.
Mm-hmm. And this is something I
learned by reading a bunch
recently. It seems to be one of the
few evidence-based, like scientifically
backed methods that actually
worked for clinical depression,
for serious depression.
- Um, yes, if we fast forward,
we're looking at in some
respects a different animal for
reasons I'll explain. Okay.
- This is unmodified ECT.
- Yeah, so we're talking about
unmodified ECT, which rules the roost
really well into the 1950s,
and some places even into the
1960s. And so it is associated
with all the problems of
fractures that we've talked about.
It's also associated with memory
problems. People often
lose memory. There's some
dispute about how serious that is,
but it's pretty widely recognized
that's one of the prices you're
going to pay for that treatment.
The thing is, for mental
hospitals in the '40s and '50s,
ECT was much more used as a
device to control people's
behavior, than as a therapeutic
intervention. It was quite punitive, seen
as such. Patients didn't want to repeat,
and so they-- ...sort of controlled
themselves a bit. But yes,
we don't know why it, quote, "works,"
but more recent work starting in
probably the 1990s -- and I'm going to get
in trouble with some people for saying this
because you mentioned patients and
psychiatrists who swear by ECT.
There are others who swear at it.
Um, partly because of the
memory problems I alluded
to, and partly because of
claims that it may cause
brain damage. Passing an electric
current through the brain is possible.
What changed ECT a bit, quite a bit
actually, was giving muscle relaxants
so that people didn't thrash about, and
the fractures were largely a thing of
the past. When you introduce these muscle
relaxers, originally they used curare,
but then they used
other, more modern drugs
to paralyze the muscles temporarily.
The problem is, that would also
paralyze your breathing muscles,
so that's not too good.
So it became a more complicated
procedure because you needed
anesthesiologists, breathing
support, and so forth
during the procedure. But
you did eliminate the
fractures. It still was a very widely
disdained practice, I think,
particularly when they had drugs
available. The thinking was that,
well, we'd sooner use those, but
the drugs turn out to be
only partially effective,
and pretty ineffective very
often for suicidal cases or in
cases of extreme melancholia.
Now, a couple of
things to say: Very often,
ECT has to be repeated at
intervals, as a kind of
maintenance therapy.
So it hasn't cured things,
but it temporarily
alleviates the symptoms, and the
temporary may be fairly lengthy, but
nonetheless, very often things will recur.
The memory problems can be quite severe.
The worries about brain
damage are, I think,
certainly things we have
to be very cautious about.
And when we talk about
treatment-resistant depression,
that's an interesting concept to
me. What it means is those are the
patients who don't respond to drugs.
They may not have a different
disease, but the drugs
don't work for them, hence
treatment resistant.
And the numbers of psychiatrists who are
willing to give ECT are rather small,
and in many states it's hedged around with
lots of legal restrictions. In
California, for example, um,
ECT now almost can't be given to
involuntarily confined patients 'cause you
have to, you have to volunteer for it.
So as-- so it's unusual in
that most medical procedures
aren't hedged about by legal
constraints like that. And
there clearly is a very
powerful group of people,
some of them psychiatrists,
many of them ex-patients,
many of them other people who just
are suspicious of modern medicine and
science, who form a group who are
very powerfully opposed to ECT. So
although it's fair to say
there are, Trials now that
seem to provide decent evidence
that for some patients
this works and that those
patients are deeply
distressed before the
treatment it's also still
a controversial treatment,
I think it's fair to say.
- Like basically every single topic, treatment,
problem subfield of psychiatry today.
- Yes, yes.
- For everything, everything we say
today, there will be at least
one person upset- ...and writing a letter.
- I think lots of people upset.
So if we talk about drugs,
there'll be two kinds of
people who will be upset,
those who think the drugs
are more powerful than they
are or who have been
successfully treated by the
drugs and go, "Well, it
worked for me, so, you know,
stop criticizing it 'cause it really
is an effective treatment." And then
on the other side of the
coin, there are those who
either the drug treatment has been
used and it's failed, or they're being
left with terrible side
effects that don't go away,
or they're part of a general
group of people that
unfortunately is of a growing number
these days who are so suspicious
of medical science and
of the drug companies
that no amount of evidence will
sway them. They are convinced that
you know, the drug
treatments are poisonous.
The Scientologists being a very extreme
example of that, who they have a whole
museum in Los Angeles and the title
is Psychiatry Industry of Death.
And then if you think about all
the resistance, for example, that
has surfaced to vaccination in
contemporary US and how the
trust in vaccination has been
destroyed for a substantial
number of people,
it's very difficult to convince
them that they're mistaken.
- And not just the trust in
vaccination consequence of that is
a general distrust in science-
- A general distrust, exactly.
- ... and distrust in medicine and so on.
- That's one of my great worries about
our contemporary situation, that we're
only-- we're less than a year in.
After four years of this,
first of all, the degree of
mistrust will have grown exponentially,
and once trust is lost, it's
very hard to recover. Secondly,
the science itself is being
destroyed. Clinical trials
that were midway through were
aborted, so that knowledge
has been lost. You would have
to start from square one, and that's years
of work. Scientists aren't being trained
because funding has been cut. Scientists
with successful careers no longer have
the funding necessary to do their work,
and it takes at least six
or seven years to train
a scientist at the
beginning of their career.
And so if you have four years
with nobody being trained,
you're talking about a decade being
lost, and what's lost is invisible--
...because it's counterfactuals.
We don't know what that science
will lead to or what that
medical treatment might
lead to, and very many
times they fail. That's
the nature of science. It's the nature of
medicine and medical research
that not every bright
idea we have is going to
eventuate in a breakthrough.
It would be really simple and wonderful
if that opposite were the case.
But the reality is we have to go
down lots of blind alleys, we
have to try lots of different
things, and we have to take
years to move from the laboratory to
practical application. And when we eliminate
a whole segment of that, and when on top
of that we diminish people's trust--
...in science, that's a
really, I think, a profoundly
devastating thing that
probably given my advanced
age, I won't live to see
the consequences of, but
my children and grandchildren
will. It really
is something cultural that
you've got to build up trust.
And it can be destroyed very easily. So
one of the things, to go back to the
very first question you asked me about, is
psychiatry in crisis? Well, genetics was
supposed to provide a clear
picture of the origins
of various mental diseases
'cause they do seem to run in
families. So the expectation
was once we decoded the
human genome and we could examine bits
and pieces of it, that we would very
quickly find a Mendelian gene or set of
genes for schizophrenia, let
us say. Hasn't happened.
We now use genome-wide association
studies, that is throwing
everything in the kitchen soup
into, into the picture, and then
without any preconditions and seeing
what relates to what. And if we
use three hundred small variations in
the genome, we can account for
about ten percent of schizophrenia.
That's not very powerful. Beyond
that, what psychiatric genetics has
tended to throw up is
something that undermines the
distinctions that we've made based
on symptomatology. So if you look,
there is a great deal of
overlap in the kinds of genetic
abnormalities that heighten
the susceptibility
to bipolar disorder or schizophrenia or
autism. There's a lot of overlap there.
What that suggests is these aren't
distinctive entities in the way
that, you know... Schizophrenia,
as my friend Robin Murray,
a British psychiatrist, has to
say, "It really seems to be the
extreme end of psychosis, the
most serious." But it's sort
of on a continuum, you know. And so if
psychiatry has to say in ten years,
as some leading psychiatrists
are speculating,
that there's no such thing as
schizophrenia, there's no such thing as
bipolar disorder, that will tend, I
suspect, to have pretty bad
effects on people's trust-
...in psychiatry, and yet that's
where the science may lead them.
So it's a complicated picture, but this
issue of, of trust and its absence
and is, is vital, I think,
in looking at not just what
we're talking about today, but
across a whole spectrum of things,
even outside the medical realm altogether.
If you lose trust in institutions,
trust in science, trust in history. So
I think more humility
and less arrogance, more
willingness to confess the limits of what
we can do, more awareness of the dangers
of enthusiasm, more skepticism when
we're told something is a breakthrough.
One of the things I worry about is the
tendency of science journalism and medical
journalism to hype things and then
When the hype turns out to be
just that, that undermines trust.
You know? So be cautious when
things come along- ... don't be
so sure that it represents a breakthrough.
I'm very worried at the moment. I see,
Ketamine and psychedelics being propounded
as a miracle cure for depression,
and the evidence for that is
enormously weak is the best
way to put it. And I've seen
this movie before too many
times. You know? I mentioned that
80% cure for Cotton's work, 80% cure
for insulin coma therapy, 80%
cure for the early asylums.
This is overblown rhetoric,
and the reality is
usually progress comes in small steps.
Sometimes it comes in big
steps. Penicillin, I think
was a huge step. Uh, I was
lucky enough to grow up
in the era when penicillin
and other antibiotics
became widely available. They
hadn't been overused by then.
And so if I had a strep throat,
I had something that got rid of
it right away. I didn't run the
risk of heart valve damage, which
in previous times would've
been the case. So you know,
once in a while you do have
these dramatic shifts,
and maybe AI will help
us in that regard, but
maybe it won't. It's another
potential double-edged sword.
- I should mention that
psychedelics, psilocybin in
particular, has been demonized for a long
time. And so there's studies now out of John
Johns Hopkins- ... that are
doing serious studies on cases
where it is effective. I
think it's nice to give a
chance to the different treatments with
the rigor of science, but with caution -
... and basically ignoring like
you're saying, science journalists
who are basically hyping every new thing
'cause they have to get clicks and all-
... this kind of stuff and-
... Look at the actual science
in the modern day. So the-
... in the past, the rigor was not
there. In the modern day, there's more.
- Yes. We can add beyond the realm of science
journalists. I think Science and Nature
make choices about what they're
gonna foreground, and they too
have this tendency to look for
things that make a big splash.
- Oh, you mean the, the editors
and the- ... the major journals.
- I think the editors, the major journals,
that's what they're looking for. As,
you know, I mean
negative findings are very important in
science. They're, they're the things that
help us avoid mistakes,
but they're not the
things that are going to get
you published in the journal.
- Right. So it's not just the
surface level science journalism.
It is also the extra journals and the
conferences and the publication process.
- Having lots of scientists working on
these problems in different
sites and different places
turns out to be very important,
I think, as a check on
enthusiasm, as a check on premature
claims that turn out to be unfounded.
And also because you're often
partially right but you're not
fully right and someone else
following the same idea-
... is, is perhaps gonna be a little
closer to the truth than you were. And so
it's, it's very helpful to have
multi-centered things and not
everything under one all-knowing- ... uh,
thing. And that's a problem
with funding agencies. The
maverick scientist has a
hard time- ... very often-
... getting a hearing. And we know of lots
of examples of that in
history where after the
fact we go "oh well yes," we
should have supported that line of
research, but we didn't."
- Uh, very well put. Let us return to,
the origins of ECT and how it was
applied. But first, if it's okay,
a quick bathroom break.
Quick ten second thank you to our sponsors.
Check them out in the description. It
really is the best way to
support this podcast. Go to
lexfridman.com/sponsors. And now dear
friends back to my conversation
with Andrew Scull. Now we're back
just to talk a little bit more about
ECT and One Flew Over the Cuckoo's
Nest. So what can we say about
that, that little cultural
moment, one of the most famous
moments about psychiatry?
First of all, Ken Kesey wrote this
book about his own experience
in a mental institution.
- Yeah, Menlo Park. Yes.
- How representative is it
of the system at the time?
- Mental hospitals have had a very
patchy and complicated history.
He was working actually in
a hospital for veterans.
Those were largely created
after the Second World War
when there were very many more
psychiatric casualties among
American troops than even the First World
War. The interesting thing is we all by
osmosis know that in the First World
War there was something called
shell shock that afflicted
the troops and that the
military initially resisted recognizing
and ultimately were forced to grasp.
But in World War II, American psychiatric
casualties among the troops were two to
three times as high as in World War I,
and that's an important part of
the history of psychiatry. But the
upshot of that was that post-war the VA
was heavily involved in,
first of all, paying to train
psychiatrists and even psychologists,
and then had in its mental hospital
system a considerable involvement
with psychiatric disorders.
Kesey-- Well, the book is different than
the film is the first thing to say.
Obviously, the film is heavily indebted to
the book, but it changes various things.
- Uh, if I may just go into
Perplexity, "The book and the
1975 film tell the same
basic story of McMurphy
challenging an oppressive psychiatric
ward, but they differ sharply in
point of view, tone, and what
the story is about. The novel is
weirder, more political, and
more about Chief Bromden's
inner world and the combine while the
film is more naturalistic, character-driven,
and turns McMurphy into the
central hero."
- Yes, I think that's right.
- McMurphy is the person that received
ECT played by Jack Nicholson.
- Yes. And you have a nurse
figure in Nurse Ratched.
- Yeah. Yeah.
- Louise Fletcher, uh, I think is
an equally powerful performance.
- It's one of the greatest films
of all time who happens to be--
which is unfortunate for,
you know, maybe psychiatry.
- Psychiatry, yes. It's very
interesting. I used to teach, um, a
class called Madness In The Movies,
and, um, I didn't just use... In fact,
I used relatively few contemporary films
and all among all the films from back
then, the one almost
everybody in the class had
seen was One Flew Over the Cuckoo's
Nest. So 18, 19, and 20-year-olds,
In two thousand and fifteen If I
showed them Alfred Hitchcock's
Spellbound, no chance they'd ever
seen that, maybe one,
because they were a class of people
interested in film. But everybody had
seen One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest.
- On that tangent really quick, what is the
greatest film on madness in your view?
- Oh, well...
- Would that be One Flew
Over the Cuckoo's Nest?
- I think One Flew Over the
Cuckoo's Nest, I think
oddly a very different film
appeared at about the same
time was I Never Promised
You a Rose Garden,
which is a much more sympathetic
portrait of a different
kind of psychiatry, a very
Freudian psychiatrist,
really about Frieda
Fromm-Reichmann who worked
at Chestnut Lodge in Maryland and treated
schizophrenia with psychotherapy
rather than with drugs
or other forms of physical intervention.
And that was a bestselling novel by a young
girl who had been her patient with
some fairly serious delusions
and a very complicated family
background, and again the film
changed a lot of things in the
novel. That's what films do. My book
Madhouse at one point interested
Hollywood, and one of the
two principals said to me, "I really
like this story. It's got a great
first act and a great second act,
but where's the third act?" Meaning,
"Where's the happy ending?" And I
had to say there wasn't any happy
ending to that story. It
was just rather grim.
- Madhouse: A Tragic Tale of
Megalomania and Modern Medicine
is the book you're referring to. Yes, that's right.
Now that reminds me of Flowers for Algernon. That
doesn't have a happy ending, and
it's not about mental health
necessarily, but it's about the
journey of institution in relation to
the health of a patient.
- Yes, Pat Barker's trilogy
of novels about World War
I was turned into a film.
I think it was called
Regeneration, and that was quite powerful.
It was about World War I and the
treatment of shell shock. Mm-hmm.
And I thought was quite well done. And my
friend Patrick McGrath, who's a novelist,
wrote a book called
Asylum. Patrick grew up
in the grounds of Broadmoor.
Broadmoor is England's
premier hospital for
the criminally insane,
and he was babysat by some of the patients.
And when you read his novels, you
can see how that upbringing affected his
rather macabre imagination. But anyway,
so One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest,
the poverty of the environment,
room that the patients were in, I think
fairly successfully recreates that
way in which staff very often put patients
down, didn't listen to them, or poked fun at
them, or even were physically
abusive, although you don't see that.
Those were all features of mental
hospitals. The general boredom of life,
sort of there, but yeah, hard to reprea--
putting boredom on the screen will
turn an audience off rather fast.
- What about nurses and this kind
of abusive element, you know?
- Yeah, I think there was an abusive
element in a lot of mental
hospitals, and it was almost
inevitable. Look at who had the
most contact with the patients:
it was the lowest paid,
least respected ward attendants,
very few even RNs, and you know,
ratio of doctor to patient in the large
state mental hospitals meant that patients
hardly ever saw a physician, you know.
Remarkable about the film,
there are many remarkable
things about the film as
well as its polemical edge,
think is that chief
psychiatrist that you see
in the film is the real head of Oregon
State Mental Hospital. He really was
introduction to acting, and I thought
he was pretty remarkable, actually.
Obviously, there's a lot
of exaggeration there, but
ECT was used in the fifties and sixties
as a tool of discipline in
the hospitals. It was also
used therapeutically, but
overwhelmingly it was used
a tool of discipline and control.
And that's true to life. Lobotomy...
One of the interesting things we haven't talked
about with all these treatments we've been
discussing is that almost invariably,
except for the case of the syphilitic
patients, for obvious reasons, men
were more troubled by that
condition than women,
it was women that got the
brunt of these experiments. So
Henry Cotton, about 70% of his
patients who were treated were
female. Lobotomy patients,
it's hard to get
overall numbers, but those
of us who've looked at
the records of a number of
different hospitals again and
again discover, again, 60 or 70%
of the patients are female. ECT
tends to be heavily female. That's
complicated by the fact that
it's used primarily as,
as we were discussing in
serious cases of depression and
so-called treatment-resistant
depression, and depression
is a diagnosis that is
more to be found among women than
men. Not that there aren't very many
men with depression, but
again, the ratio is such. Men
tend to get a different--
they get different diagnoses.
Personality disorders, for example, are
very, very common and are more a male
diagnosis. Um, ADHD- ...is more
male than female and so on. So
it's good to point that
out. Uh, I think it helped
end interest in ECT, except for a
small handful of enthusiasts
for decades, that film.
Um, and probably even now it creates
hesitation in people about the
treatment. So it's one that has
had a very powerful and
long-lasting effect, I think.
- I think the surprising thing is I
recently learned a friend of mine tried
everything, about 20 years
ago, tried everything to
--with depression, and ECT is the last
thing he tried, and it changed his life-
...for the better.
- That's not an uncommon story. Yeah.
- And then I looked online and
there's a lot of stories like this.
And I-- before learning of that, my, I'm
embarrassed to say, knowledge of ECT
was just "One Flew Over
the Cuckoo's Nest."
- You know, it has a terrible history-
in the, in the '40s, '50s and
'60s. There are lots of,-
- Abuses
- Uh, the CIA funded Ewen
Cameron up in Canada,
and he was giving multiple ECTs a day and
reducing peoples to...
Well, they couldn't walk,
they couldn't talk, they couldn't feed
themselves, they were incontinent, and then he
built them back up, or so he claimed, but
in many cases, they were left permanently
damaged. So I could recite lots
of real horror stories about ECT,
but it's also, if you're
honest about the thing,
what you just described, that is patients
who were on the brink of suicide,
who had long-running
depressions, some of them
had ECT and they describe it as lifesaving.
And as I say when more controlled
trials have been done recently,
there's enough evidence now that
it's hard to say, "This never
works. This is just one of these
desperate remedies we should consign to
dark ages." The complicating thing is
we'd have no clue why it works.
It's a purely empirical treatment.
- Right. Right.
- And that itself I think
tends to put people off.
If you have a curable form of
cancer and the surgeon says,
"Well, I'm gonna remove it," and she does,
that's that. But because we understand
even a little bit, even if our
knowledge of human biology is pretty
primitive, we do understand
a little bit that cancer is
cells dividing uncontrollably
and taking up and doing
damage to the body and
eventually killing you,
and the fact that we can
surgically remove it is a big
deal. There are lots of disorders.
I have high blood pressure.
If untreated, my blood pressure is like
a 20-year-old's thanks to treatment.
It's an ongoing thing. I take the
damn pill every day and it has a
few minor side effects, but
for me very minor ones. And it
turns what could have killed me
via a stroke or a heart attack
into a condition that's
very well controlled. So,
you know, it-- All of these things,
they're, they're complicated picture-
It's easy with some of these
things, with lobotomy,
with insulin comas, deep sleep treatments,
Henry Cotton's endeavors.
Those you can just say,
"Well, we'll throw them away."
And for a long time, I think ECT
would have formed part of that cast
of characters. So when I first
conceived the idea of writing
Desperate Remedies, the book,
it was back in 1981 and I was in London
on a Guggenheim Fellowship at the
Wellcome Institute. And I hadn't done
research in detail, but I was
aware there were all these things
lurking about that had happened in
the 1920s and '30s and I thought
that would be a very
interesting thing to study. And
luckily I didn't do it right away or
I did it piecemeal over the years
and I ended up writing a much
more comprehensive look at
psychiatry really from its origins to now.
And I couldn't have written that
book back then, and I would've
missed all the developments
from 1980 onwards, which are
very, very important to the,
to the overall picture.
- So forty years later, 2022.
- Yes. Yes, exactly.
- Your own Desperate Remedies: Psychiatry's-
- Yeah. Yeah
- ... Turmoil in Quest to
Cure Mental Illness.
- I've written a lot of books
and, and along the way--
part of the way, I think I've
been productive and kept
interested. I always had two... at
least two projects on the go at once.
You can't simultaneously write two
things, but I'd have one and I'd work
on it, and if I got tired of it, I'd pick up
the other one for a bit and then go back.
And it also meant when I was
working on one main project, I had
other things percolating in, in my head,
and I would, I would come
across things that were
relevant to them and I'd make a note and
then I'd go back. So when I finally did
Desperate Remedies, I'd been thinking
about those issues for forty years,
and that made a big difference,
I think, to the way I approached
things and to what I thought.
Uh, 'cause you just... You
either like Thomas says, you say
the same thing over and over
and over again for forty years or
you learn new things and you
broaden what you know, and you
think about things in a different
way because you realize you
haven't grasped the full complexity
of what you're looking at.
And so look, what I found with
psychiatry is there are really
a couple of fundamental things that
have kept me engaged with the field.
One, it's an arena where
there's tremendous human
suffering, and it spreads out and it's
as far as I know -- and I wrote a big
book called Madness in Civilization
about from the ancient Greeks and
ancient China to now -- in every
society I've studied they have
to cope with this. It takes
different forms. It's regarded
in different ways. It's treated
differently, but that there
are people that deviate
so far from the norm of what we
regard as culturally appropriate,
they exist everywhere. So the suffering,
the difficulty of studying it,
and then the fact that it is such
a complex and difficult
subject to understand.
The very fact that we have
such limits to our knowledge
means there's space there to
examine things in a, in a
very in what needs to be
a very complicated way.
And so it's, it's intellectual puzzles
attracted some very, very smart
people, but there's a long way to go.
- Yeah, we have glimmers of insights
about how the, mind works but-
....if you s-, if you look at the span of
human history, we're probably in the very
early days of understanding this
particular one. I have to, if it's okay-
- Yes, of course
- ...so that we've been carrying
multiple threads together. One
of the threads that I think,
uh, is really exciting to
me and really important to the history
of psychiatry is the psychotherapy side.
We have mentioned the psychopharmacology
that will also-- it would
be nice to discuss when the two clash
and there's a revolution where phar--
Psychopharmacology kinda wins over
psychoanalysis for a time. But let us start
at the somewhat beginning,
in the nineteenth century
when talk therapy starts
coming to life maybe in the
religious context with Christian Science
and then psychoanalysis context.
- Yes. So I'd mentioned late nineteenth
century psychiatry confined as it
was to the mental hospital and
to people incarcerated in
those places had become very
biological. But there were people
experiencing mental troubles of
various kinds, sadness, confusion,
loss of social relationships
that were troubling them,
grief, all sorts of things
like that, that didn't
involve time in a mental
hospital but nonetheless
involved a good deal of distress
as they continued to do.
And one of the things that was interesting
about nineteenth century America
is it spawned a number of new
religions, sort of variants
of Christianity. So you
had Seventh Day Adventists
group that still exists who actually
spawned a sanitarium for their depressed
congregants that was
later taken over by two
prominent members of the Adventist
Church, the Kellogg family.
everybody knows them through cereal.
But they ran a huge sanitarium to which
Abraham Lincoln's widow went, Tarzan went,
Henry Ford went, lots of very
prominent industrialists
and politicians and, you
know, it was kind of a
a farm to go and recover
your mental stability and
health and it was all bound up
also with beliefs about diet and
defecation and all sorts
of things. There were the
Mormons or Church of Jesus Christ
of Latter-day Saints. Many
Christians don't believe they're really
Christian but they think they are and
call themselves such. So you have
a number of these and one of them
was Christian Science, which was the
invention of a woman named Mary Baker Eddy.
Developed the idea, and there are still
Christian Science churches and Christian
Science reading rooms all across America,
that there wasn't such a thing as
disease. That it could be prayed
away; that it was just a lack of
sufficient faith. So faith healing,
tended to work, I think,
better if it worked at all for
psychiatric problems than it did if you
had, say, cancer. But Christian Science
achieved a considerable
number of followers
disproportionately women but not
only women. And it began to treat
many of the people suffering from
what we would think of as the milder
mental disorders. And it attracted
both adherents and severe
critics. Mark Twain, for
example, was thoroughly dismissive of
Mary Baker Eddy. But it was
very successful for a time.
There were other religiously
based attempts to
join in. The most important
of which in New England was
something called Emmanuel Movement
centered around the Church of the
Emmanuel in Boston, which was an
attempt actually initially to
bring medical and religious approaches
to helping the mentally troubled.
Rather quickly, the doctors
involved decided this
was veering too much in the
direction of medically-based
therapeutics. They kind of withdrew from
enterprise. It dispensed-- There were
talk therapies obviously with a strong
religious component around them.
This was also at a time when some...
guess we can call them psychiatrists,
they were often neurologists,
were beginning to get lots of
patients with these kinds of
difficult to treat disorders. Neurology had
emerged in America after the Civil War.
Civil War provided a lot of naturalistic
experiments on what happens to the
human brain and the human nervous
system when trauma affect -
I don't mean psychological
trauma, I mean bullets blowing
holes in your brain. A
group of new specialists
emerged after the Civil War who
claimed expertise in the
brain and the nervous system.
Well, one of the other side parts of that
is insanity, because insanity is also seen
as a brain disease. So there is a
conflict that erupts in the 1870s and
'80s between neurologists
and psychiatrists.
But the neurologist can't, for the most
part, get into the asylum where the most
seriously ill patients
are. Gradually, what
comes to their waiting room
along with people like multiple
sclero-- suffering from things like
multiple sclerosis are people with
functional mental disorders. There's the
beginning of an outpatient practice,
um which initially involves
some drugs, the use of
electricity. Not ECT, but
the use, for example, of
static electricity, because
it produces obvious
physiological responses. Electricity is seen
as dominating the workings of the body.
Sometimes tonics of one sort or
another. Most notoriously of
all, something called the rest cure.
Silas Weir Mitchell, one of
the leading lights of American
neurology, develops complete bedrest,
lots of calories, lots of food, complete
lack of intellectual stimulation.
Supposedly, this is going
to cure you. Mainly aimed at women. I
feel like that's another evidence-backed
technique that works well.
Well, you know, I've
partaken in this and I
know it has helped me.
Laying in bed doing nothing, eating
snacks. Virginia Woolf was one of the
people subjected to this. She claimed
it practically drove her mad or
made her worse, you know? Just to clarify, we're
talking about laying in bed, eating snacks.
Eating lots of snacks. Very
high calorie. Okay, Weir
Mitchell wrote two popular bestsellers,
self-help books, suppose you'd call
them in the modern genre. One was
called Wear and Tear. The pace of
modern life, the telegraph, the
railway was all too much.
Your nervous system was
overstressed. Either your
batteries ran down, that was
one analogy, or you overtaxed
your system and went bankrupt.
Wear and tear, that was
the problem. The solution
was Fat and Blood. That was
the title of the other book.
You got scrawny, nouveau,
nervous, twitchy.
And what you really needed was
to build back up your strength.
including your nervous strength.
Isn't it fascinating to look at that?
120 years plus ago? They're talking about
how anxiety inducing society
is, how much is going on.
And we in the modern day talk in exact same way about
social media, the internet, all that kind of stuff.
Yeah, yeah, it is. We look back on the nineteenth century and think of it in idyllic terms of a much slower pace of life, and people, they thought it was stressful in exactly the ways we
do. There was a class of potential patients. Some of them were seeking help in the neurologists and a few psychiatrists who moved out of the asylum. But there were also these mental healing
groups that were religious,
and they're all around
at the beginning of the 20th century.
And in 1909, a Viennese gentleman
and two of his close
colleagues travel across the
Atlantic on a German
steamer and arrive in New
York and then transport themselves
up to Worcester, Massachusetts,
where Clark University is
celebrating its 20th anniversary.
Clark University was then set
up-- it still exists, but it was
set up to copy the German
research university. The
only comparable example at the time was
Johns Hopkins in Baltimore, and Hopkins
developed the leading
medical school of the time
borrowing from that German concept of mixing
research and teaching and patient care.
- I like how you're telling
this in a cinematic way
the story of Sigmund Freud and Carl Jung--
...coming to America to give a
lecture. I like, I like how it's like
the movie opens and there, yeah. Yeah, well, here
he is, you know, like, how do you feel who he
is? He's fairly obscure. We should say the
reason you're actually telling it that
way is America has been a really
defining place for psychiatry.
Yes. And then Freud had his own views
on America and so on. But this--
this was, in terms of the history, yes,
psychiatric medicine, America as central.
Right. Many of the in-house
histories of psychiatry
portray this as Freud conference.
But it wasn't. Freud was almost an
afterthought of the conference.
Um, the head of Clark was
a psychologist, and he was
interested in Freud,
but actually there were
about thirty speakers at
the Clark conference, two
Nobel Prize winners in
physics, Franz Boas, who
was the leading anthropologist
of his generation, and a
host of other scholars,
including a couple of Freud's
fierce critics, one of whom,
Stern, was on the same boat as
him. And they avoided one another
like the plague. But anyway, it's
important to see that, and
Freud, it's a mark of how
important German science and German
medical science was in the late
nineteenth, early twentieth century,
where it was THE most advanced
in the world, that Freud
delivered his lectures IN GERMAN,
AND THE AUDIENCE, THAT WASN'T A PROBLEM FOR
THE AUDIENCE 'CAUSE THEY'D ALL LEARNED GERMAN
so they could read German
literature on medicine. So quite an
extraordinary thing. Um
William James attends
one of Freud's lectures and has
a conversation with him. William
James is one of the people thinking
about the psychology of the
human mind in interesting ways. He's not
impressed by Freud, and he also has a bad
heart condition. He dies not
all that long afterwards, but
he's not impressed by Freud.
A handful of people are,
some of the neurologists. And
Freud's lectures explicitly
attack religiously based
psychotherapy, says
psychotherapy is like a surgical operation
on the mind. And only us doctors
or only us thoroughly trained
people cause actually he
doesn't believe that psychoanalysis is
only something that can be practiced
by medically qualified,
but the lecture is on
psychoanalysis. Yes, it's
five lectures. They're
published subsequently, and
he makes a very important
convert there. Um James Jackson Putnam is
a Boston Brahmin, one of the upper-class
Bostonians who's extremely
well connected and is
professor of neurology at
Harvard, and he becomes a
Freudian at that conference. So
mainstream American psychiatry
pays very little attention to to
Freud's arrival on the scene.
And when he becomes a bit more visible,
they tend to be very dismissive. They uh
They regard the idea of talk therapy for
something they regard as a biological
condition as a ridiculous idea.
Maybe just uh mention a few
things. Sigmund Freud, of course, is
widely acknowledged to be the father of
psychoanalysis. And uh he has
a bunch of ideas, one of which
is there's this unconscious
mind that is the source of many
of our uh behaviors. Exactly. And
then psychoanalysis is a way to
delve deep into that mind,
and the tools he used to do
that is talking. Yes, Freud was
trained as a neurologist himself
uh and studied under the most famous late
Nineteenth-century
neurologist Charcot in Paris
and translated Charcot into
German and endeared himself to
Charcot, by doing that,
that's, um, a clever way to
help your career along. But his
Viennese colleagues didn't think
much of Charcot, and they didn't
think much of Freud's ideas either.
So he had a bit of a hard time,
but he did develop a successful
practice in the sense that patients
came to him. He was accompanied by
two of his close disciples to the Clark
conference, one of them Carl Jung.
was then anointed the crown
prince. He was supposed
to inherit Freud's enterprise until the men
had a very serious falling out, mm-hmm, uh
just a little bit later in 1913, and
Freud and Jung went their separate ways.
That's a complicated story.
Freud, as one of his
close, uh, friends and
collaborators, put it, was a great
Hater, if you fell out with
Freud, it was bad news.
hater. If you fell out with Freud, it was bad news. Oh yeah, yeah,
you were excommunicated if it was Adler, but Jung especially.
- Jung was Swiss and he worked
in the major mental hospital
in Zurich, and he was attracted to
psychoanalysis and to Freud.
And for the first few
years there, there was this
obvious close alliance.
Anyway, so Jung was the person who
actually persuaded Freud to go
to America. Freud initially--
Freud had a very low opinion of
America. He said it should
be renamed Dollaría because
it was only interested in the dollar.
And American women were far too
pushy and powerful, and American food
was dreadful and it poisoned him, and
on and on. Um--
- So as you said, Freud was a master hater.
- Yeah, he was. And one of the things
he hated was America, even though
America brought him some
fairly rich patients. But--
...the richest patients of all
went to Jung, not to Freud.
Um, and I think that probably
exacerbated this split.
- Let's actually focus first before the
conference on the actual ideas of
psychoanalysis. So Freud was the
originator of psychoanalysis. This is
19th century. So tell me about
the original case of Anna
O. and like what is psychoanalysis?
- Yeah. So Freud's academic career
had been failing in Vienna,
and he faced a prospect of
either having to emigrate to
America, which he regarded
with horror in the 1880s,
or perhaps reviving his
career by going and
studying under the most famous neurologist
of the era, Jean-Martin Charcot,
who was then delivering
lectures on hysteria in Paris.
And so Freud went and
spent some months there
and came back imbued with
Charcot's ideas about hysteria
and found a Viennese medical establishment.
He started a consulting career
and that involved-- He had a
close friend named Josef Breuer.
And Breuer was more senior, had a very
large practice, and referred patients to
Freud. And the two of them began
to be interested in this problem
of hysteria. Breuer had treated
a woman who's now known as the sort
of foundation patient for-- the
Ur patient for psychoanalysis,
who was known to us as Anna O.
She-- We actually know she was
Bertha von Pappenheim, but that was
hidden for a long time. A
lot of these patients had
pseudonyms because obviously the cases
exposed a lot about their inner psychology
and quite reasonably,
even without the modern
concerns about privacy, there was
a reluctance to identify them.
So Anna O. had nursed her father. She was
Breuer's patient, not Freud's.
She'd nursed her father through an
illness, and he'd ended up dying, and she
developed various physical
symptoms that troubled
her a great deal and was also somewhat
depressed. And Breuer and Freud
dealt with that by developing
a notion that what she was
suffering from was repressed
memories and trauma.
And this would become central
to psychoanalysis, the
idea of half-muttered memories
lurking in your subconscious
that emerged in distorted forms of
psychological symptoms and ways
of being in the world that
were disruptive. Freud, of
course, develops a much more
elaborate theory of this
in years to come. And
Breuer collaborate on a book
called Studies in Hysteria,
and they're a series of case vignettes
in there of patients Freud has treated.
And he develops the notion
that people have these
past experiences. Initially, he thinks
they're real, that they're-- For
example, they have been
sexually assaulted as a child,
and that they can't face that,
and so they hide it away
from themselves. But they can't
completely, so it emerges in this tortured
series of forms. And
as things develop, the notion of
resistances emerges, that you can't easily
retrieve these memories,
and indeed, you resist them
surfacing, and you have a hard
time acknowledging them. And only
with long and painful work will it
become possible for-- But as you
bring them into-- from the
unconscious into the conscious world,
you learn to cope with them in a
different way and, and your personality
is transformed and you're made better.
- But crucially, the stuff that
happens in childhood is important.
- Yes. The early experiences have a dramatic
effect, and I think even some biological
psychiatrists would agree with
that notion these days. That,
you know, to the extent we abolish
this distinction between mind and
body and, and acknowledge that they
are closely tied together, um,
traumatic experiences in
childhood, various socialization
experiences, loss and so on deeply mark the
human psyche, I think, and, and can have
long-term effects that
are, are very powerful.
- Of course Freud added a bunch
of stuff in the realm of
psychosexual stages of childhood.
- Yes. As he begins to develop
his theories, he more and more
comes to see at first the libido, which gets
sort of transformed into the sex drive-
... And sexual experiences
and the repression of
sexuality and the modification
of sexuality as people grow.
Um, all of that enters the picture.
It's one of the things that
ends up dividing Freud and
Jung, Jung somewhat because
Jung downplays that sexual side
of things after the break.
Um, but so Freud develops a very
complicated theory of mind initially
reflecting his training as a neurologist.
He tries to write an essay which
survives called Project for a
Scientific Psychology, and the
scientific psychology is gonna
tie psychology back into neurology.
But he abandons that, and
once he's abandoned that,
he goes on to develop increased...
an increasingly elaborate theory. He
writes The Interpretation of
Dreams, for example, because he
begins to regard dreams as an arena where
these hidden memories, these suppressed-
... things reemerge in disguised
form in your dream life. And so
that book marks an important
step forward. He becomes
interested in things like slips of the
tongue, so-called Freudian mistakes.
As seeing those as revealing
what really is hidden from you.
And so there's this very elaborate
dissection of things that relies upon
long extended talk therapy.
- Of course underlying it he's building a
model of how this whole
mind thing works. There's-
... three interacting parts of the
personality. First the id, which is the
primitive entirely unconscious
driven by pleasure principle seeking
immediate gratification or basic
drives such as sex and aggression.
There's the ego, which
is the rational mediator
operating under reality principle
balancing the id's demands with
external reality. And
finally, the super ego,
which is the internalized moral
standards and ideals producing
guilt or pride and striving for
perfection. So that's the structure.
- Yeah. That is broadly speaking the
structure that Freud ends up with,
and the conflicts between
these entities and
the ways they interact are
obviously the thing that
creates your mental universe, your
way of being in the world and
in many cases creates pathology, which
through the process of
psychoanalysis you can transform
grotesque unhappiness into ordinary
unhappiness or something like that.
You know? So-
- Yeah, sure
- Yes, you get that. And initially,
Jung gets one of the heirs to the International
Harvester fortune as a patient, and,
um, the McCormick family are
as rich as the Rockefellers
and the Carnegies and the, you know,
the Vanderbilts of that world.
This guy is a US senator
who ends up committing
suicide in nineteen twenty-five
after a lot of treatment from,
from Jung when he fails to win
reelection to the US Senate. He
kills himself in Washington in
the interregnum. But he also gets
another one of that brood. One
of the Rockefeller daughters,
Edith Rockefeller marries a McCormick.
And she has a lot of psychological
issues, and she tries
to get Jung to move to Chicago
promising him she'll set him up
in a mansion with lots of her
friends as his patients,
and Jung has no interest.
So then she finally persuades him to come
to New York and accompany
her on the liner across to
Zurich to be treated.
She's agoraphobic, and
so she has a hard time being
out, out of her little cocoon.
So she's treated there as an
example of how peculiar she was. I
mentioned the agoraphobia. So she occupies
a huge array of suites with all her
servants and so on in
Zurich. And she takes a
train journey, it's stopping
train, and her chauffeur
follows the train in the Rolls Royce in
case she has to jump out of the train at
a station 'cause she can't bear
it anymore. And she becomes a
Jungian analyst, but she's
very wealthy and she writes
big checks to Jung which is the
important thing. And then Jung
attracts Paul Mellon and his wife Mary.
And so Jung's works are
published by Princeton
University Press with a subvention
from that Mellon Foundation.
So it's a long-running
thing. Freud doesn't get
patients quite that rich. He
gets some rich Americans.
- We should say that Freud became--
Freud's ideas became quite
popular among the intellectual and artist
class in the nineteen twenties in America.
- And another thing
happened. World War I saw
the breakdown of many soldiers
from something that came
to be labeled as shell shock. The label
shell shock intimates its, the first
theories about its origin, which
was that shells bursting near
you and bombs bursting near you
shook up your body and your
brain and created some
physical damage that then
accounted for the symptoms of shell
shock: your mutism, your blindism, your
constant shaking, your
nightmares, all of that.
But it became increasingly apparent that
shell shock was actually a
psychological thing. The trauma of war
in significant number of cases
brought about mental breakdowns.
And in thinking about that,
Freud's ideas about the
unconscious mind and
trauma and its connection
to symptomatology acquired
a new significance
for a lot of people in that
period. And then after the war,
you're absolutely right among a certain
smart section of society, those
ideas developed a considerable purchase.
Psychiatrists who were
mostly stuck in the asylums
dealing with psychotic patients
wanted nothing to do with these
ideas and this talk
therapy. The mainstream
psychotherapy which was
mostly in a clinical setting
Yeah, Freud's ideas were not popular. No.
The only partial exception to that was
The mental hospital in
Washington DC--the only federal
mental hospital, St. Elizabeths.
William Alanson White,
who was then the superintendent, was
somewhat sympathetic to Freud's ideas and
tried a bit, but you're
talking about thousands
of patients and the idea of talk
therapy for them is obviously out of
reach, plus they are much more severely
disturbed, so it does happen. Novelists,
painters, artists, playwrights,
uh and the audience for
those elite forms of culture
do tend to embrace Freudian ideas. Sex
sells in the theater and on the movies. Um,
obviously. But beyond that, part of Freud's
appeal to everybody, it was something he
lamented at one point. He said, "You know,
my case histories read like short
stories. Like works of fiction.
And in that sense, people think they
lack the stamp of serious science.
But I'm driven to that because that's
how I unpack what's going on."
Well, psychoanalysis is telling
stories. It's getting people to recover
stories, recover memories,
to rebuild, right?
Um, and its elements of psychological
conflict and hidden motives and so forth
naturally very appealing to people writing
novels. People writing plays.
People doing screenplays." And
for artists of the modern sort
the idea that we can extract things from
the subconscious Surrealism and the
like, for example, are clearly
very heavily influenced by
Freudian ideas But it's
important to know circa
1930 there are probably three hundred
psychoanalysts in North America.
if they each Classical psychoanalysis
involving five hours a week
They can't treat that many
patients A few thousand
when there are hundreds of thousands
in the hospitals Right Mm-hmm So
what changes that Hitler
starts killing off Jews
and killing off psychoanalysts
The ones who can
escape some of them go to
England and some come to America
the most famous escapee is
Freud himself and his daughter
Anna Who Princess Bonaparte who's one of
Freud's great supporters
bribes the Nazis to get him
out And he travels by train
to London Very sick with
cancer of the jaw As he has
been since the mid-'20s
So he sets up shop in London
and Anna succeeds him really
as one of the central figures in
British psychoanalysis But other
analysts come here to America So
the numbers of analysts probably by
1940 America's not yet in
the war have a bit more than
doubled And more
importantly psychoanalytic
training has become much more
organized here The institutes
outside the universities
control psych... And
universities are not yet the knowledge
factories they become after the
war mm-hmm And that's
a crucial mistake that
psychoanalysis makes It's great because
it controls its training completely
The bad thing is when the center
of gravity moves to the university
it's not there and either resists being
incorporated or the university resists
incorporating it So I think that's
a structural weakness for that
But what really transforms
things is World War II Five
fifty minute hours famously They last
fifty minutes 'cause then there's
ten ten minutes for four analysts to recover
before the next patient arrives Yes You
are free associating on the couch
and gradually being coaxed
to see as material emerges
what you're hiding from yourself
I mean initially they tried This is in
their early early days That they tried
hypnosis yes But they've You know this
is where Freud took the big leap and
expanded free association
Right So I mentioned
Freud training under Charcot Charcot
hypnotized his hysterical patients
We now know a lot of that was
fakery Not I don't think he
was conscious of the fakery
but the patients were on
display over and over again and they
worked their routines up very well and
they deceived him and they deceived
the audience But Freud came back from
Paris bringing with him the idea
that hypnosis was the way forward
But after the break with
Breuer Breuer had a general
medical practice and lost interest in
hysteria and didn't want anything to do with
the revisions of Freud's work on hysteria
After that happened Freud who was a very
clumsy hypnotist by his own account
began to develop this
alternative of free association
and getting people to speak
whatever came into their head
without a censor. That was
the important thing, that the
half-murdered memories were being
hidden from you and your-- uh,
the constellation of psychological
forces in your unconscious was
squashing them down but they were
reemerging as other kinds of symptoms
- So how well does psychoanalysis work? How
much do we understand? We've talked about
all these approaches that didn't work.
How well did it work at that time?
- You know, one of the things after
World War II when psychoanalysis
was making great strides in America
and the Rockefeller Foundation was
still heavily involved in
promoting psychiatry and
developing what it hoped
would be new tools in it
The then heads of the institute-- Of the
funding program, Alan
Gregg and Robert Morison,
especially Morrison, kept
pressing the analysts:
"Provide us proof that what you do works."
And the analyst kept resisting and
resisting and resisting, saying
"It's much more complicated than
that. There's no easy measure because
what we're doing is reconstructing entire
personalities, entire ways of being."
Sense People sense themselves,
their ways of being in the world.
"And we don't have easy
ways to measure that."
- To contrast that with the
80% promises over and
over and over and over. Yes, yes, yes.
- And it's a long and complicated pro...
That was very important. Because
another kind of psychotherapeutics is
emerging in, in the aftermath, during
and in the aftermath of the
war as a rival for both
psychiatry and for
psychoanalysis. Initially
not terribly successful,
but as time goes on,
a more and more important part of the
story. So to focus on the war for a minute,
Um, America's psychiatrists
went to the military
brass and to the politicians
before America entered the
war, and it had some advance warning
because America didn't enter till
Pearl Harbor, but the European war
had been going on. And they said,
"Look, if we have to fight, we're gonna
have the same problem we had in the
First World War. We're gonna
train these soldiers, gonna equip
them, we're gonna put them
in the battlefield and the
psychologically vulnerable among
them are gonna break down."
"They'll be shell shock all over again,
so we should screen all recruits to make
sure they're not psychologically
weak and susceptible."
And they screen out 1 3/4 million people
and say, "These men are not
fit. So now we won't have the
problems we had in World War I." Except
it quickly turns out that those
problems reemerge. Industrial warfare
exposes people to seeing
things and doing things
that all of us in normal
life would recoil from.
And when we're forced to do
them as soldiers, many of us--
Can't speak from experience, but from talking
to people who've gone through all this--
Uh, many of them find the experiences and
the memories those create intolerable.
And they emerge in symptoms
and they break down.
So it became a huge problem for the
American Army, as it did for all
the armies. Actually, the
Nazis just shot people.
Broke down, bang, you're dead.
We're not dealing with you.
But, um, obviously the Allies, that was
not the response. Um, and they quickly had
to try to treat these troops, maybe
get them back into the fighting
lines, maybe get them
into support positions.
Something to cope with the
problem, which was both, um,
created extraordinary morale
problems among the troops
and it invited malingering,
claiming you had these
conditions when you didn't. It obviously
cost a lot of the fighting force.
In combat conditions, as much
as 25% of the soldiers broke
down. So it was a big, big problem.
Before the war, there were about 2,000
psychiatrists in North America, in the US.
At the end of the war, there were more
than 2,000 psychiatrists in the US
military. Okay, so you had to
train people in a hurry, um,
and even still, it was
hard to get enough people
trained. And it turned
out that the head of the
US military, not the first, but
the first one died, the second
one uh was a man named
William Menninger from the
Menninger Clinic in Kansas,
where he and his brother
ran a psychoanalytic treatment facility.
So Bill Menninger became the
head of Army psychiatry.
He concluded that the best treatment
for these soldiers breaking
down was psychotherapeutic in
nature. The origin of their
condition was trauma, uh, and so
in a watered-down way, Freud's
ideas, those were the ones
that the people that recruited
quickly and retrained as psychiatrists
absorbed. So they formed after the war
a fairly coherent group of people,
separate from the psychiatrists in
the state hospitals who were still
very biologically oriented.
Another group emerged during the war
precisely because you couldn't produce enough
psychotherapists who were MDs quickly
enough. Psychologists were drafted in
and asked to treat. So what the
psychologists discovered was,
"Hey, we could do this stuff too, and
we really like it." "It's interesting-"
"...it's challenging.
We should do that." So
after the war, similar kind of problem.
Mental illness is a massive problem. The
returning soldiers, it's a big problem,
but it's also a problem
in the community. Um,
these guys don't... The psychiatrists
don't go and work in the
mental hospital. They start
outpatient treatment. And by
1958, about 80% of
psychiatrists are working in
outpatient rather than
in the hospitals, right?
So the psychologists organize
themselves and federal
money -- Again, "We need you.
We need you. We need more of
you." So the VA, the Veterans
Administration, and then once
the National Institute of
Mental Health is established, they
start providing a lot of money
for training, and they train not
just psychiatrists, they train
psychologists. So the question is:
How are the psychologists gonna set
up clinical training?
So what the psychologists come
up with, the clinically oriented
ones, is a training program where would-be
clinical psychologists spend two years
learning basic scientific psychology
and research methods, and then
they have two or three years
of clinical work and an experience.
And that's very clever because
it means when they start looking
for grants, they know how to
do that, and the psychoanalysts don't
have a clue how to apply for federal
grant money, and they
don't get any almost.
Beyond that, these people begin to work on
treating symptoms. The psychoanalysts
think to treat a symptom is to
play Whac-A-Mole. If you don't
deal with the underlying
problems of the personality, their
interaction between your id ego and superego,
you suppress that symptom, and
another one will pop up over here.
The clinical psychologists go, "We're
gonna treat the symptoms of what
are troubling people. We're gonna treat
the symptoms, and we're gonna develop
techniques that allow people
to cope with those symptoms
and eliminate them." And how are we
gonna do that? We're going to do it
primarily through what initially is
cognitive behavioral therapy and
later interpersonal therapy and some other
variants emerge. But basically, what
they try to do with those techniques is
develop things that work relatively quickly,
work specifically on one set of
problems or small subset of problems,
and try to get those under
control. And how does
it work? You've developed
really bad habits.
You... The way you react
to being socially snubbed
or being ignored or the way you
deal with your coworkers or the
trouble you're having with
your disruptive child
will help you see the patterns
that you've fallen into
and will give you exercises
that will work to give
you a better way of coping with those
things that don't produce these
symptoms. I'm oversimplifying
obviously, but basically that's the
fundamental thrust of this.
- And one of the other contrasting things
about CBT, Cognitive Behavioral Therapy,
is that it doesn't have necessarily that
heavy requirement of five hours a week.
- Exactly. So these therapies could be
packaged. They could be reproduced.
They could be tested to
see whether they worked,
so they had an evidentiary foundation. The
psychoanalyst would say, "It's gonna take
us years, and it's hard to measure."
These guys went, "Well, we'll
measure what happens when
we treat people this way?"
- Psychologists.
- Uh, yeah. The symptoms are what matter,
not the underlie-- you know, the
underlying more complex thing that
psychoanalysts claimed to be treating.
And so it's shorter. It's reproducible
whereas psychoanalytic-- You know, every
patient is a new patient, a new-- with a
new set of complicated things going
on. Here we are. We're gonna do this.
- And the key figures here are Albert
Bandura, Albert Ellis, Aaron Beck.
- Yes. Um, Bandura and
some other psychologists
launching this movement, and then
later on Aaron Beck, who went by
Tim Beck who just recently died at... I
think he was ninety-nine. Extraordinary.
- No, no, I think he crossed 100.
- Maybe 100. Yeah. Maybe 100.
- There's videos of him talking at that
age and he's still, he's still killing
it, so wise.
- Aaron Beck is a remarkable
figure because he was
also one of the first in the 1960s
to look at psychiatric diagnosis
and show how unreliable it
was, how-- how difficult
it was to get psychiatrists
to agree on what was wrong.
- So he was a psychoanalyst, right?
- He had been trained as
a psychoanalyst, became
disillusioned with it, and so there
were two strands, two important
strands that stemmed from
his work. First, this...
He was one of the ones
within the community itself
who said to his fellow
psychiatrists, "You know, we're
not very good at this diagnosis business--"
"... and maybe we need to work on that."
Okay? And that was very important
for the movement towards DSM-III.
The other side of the coin was
he broke with the idea that treating
symptoms was a waste of time,
and joined with the
psychologists who already
embarked on that journey to say, "How
can we develop techniques to overcome
these self-destructive ways in which
people are responding? How can we help
with their ability to
interact?" So interpersonal
therapy is, you know, much more
concerned with the way in which
if your relations with other
people break down, that
damages your emotional stability. If you
repair those relationships,
that helps your emotional
stability come back. So all of this
develops, and Americans are unusual. The--
Most of the rest of the world has
what we call socialized medicine.
Um, America doesn't have that, so
we're used to paying for medical care.
And so Americans were more willing, I
think, to pay for clinical psychologists,
and they attacked some of the
problems of everyday living, the more
uh, I was gonna say minor, but these
are often quite distressing things. But
those were-- those were the things they
were most successful at doing. If I
look at the literature on
CBT, for example, and its
uses in cases of schizophrenia,
the evidence is pretty
poor that it works. And even the evidence
for the milder conditions is a bit more
ambiguous than we like...
That they like to pretend.
The Cochrane Reviews, which
are a systematic attempt to
assess how strong the
evidence for particular
approaches to disease
of all sorts are, say
that at best, the evidence
for CBT is of low and
medium confidence, you
know? But I think, again,
there are patients for
whom this helps, and
indeed, for the milder forms of
depression, I think CBT works better
than the drugs without some of
the side effects that the, the
drugs have. And indeed, NICE, which is the
British organization that
passes on what treatments
the National Health Service
will support and which
ones are, are sufficiently evidence-based
has come to that same conclusion.
- So I think one thing to just say about
cognitive behavioral therapy, I mean, it's--
It has some elements of kind of surface
level intuitive kind of things like--
... being aware of and adjusting
your thought patterns, being
aware of triggers that get
you-- down a negative spiral--
- Exactly
- ... and then basic behavior changes,
habit changes that lead to a healthier
life. So I think, I think this kinda,
you know, getting your life
together kind of process-
... is intuitive that that would
have a positive effect on some
percent of the population. But as you
get more serious and serious into the
land of mental disorders, it starts
to be a little bit less conclusive.
- Yes. I think that's an accurate
statement of what-- the way
I read the literature. And
it's not a cure-all, but
for some patients, this really
does seem to improve things
quite a lot. And it does
make sense that you
have developed poor ways of responding
to signals from the outside world,
and they've become habitual, and
they've -- habits, as we know, are very
hard to break.
You know, there's a lot of homework, there's
a lot of exercises you have to do to try
to reconfigure the ways
you deal with the world.
And it's not for everybody, and it doesn't
work for everybody, but there's some
set, subset of people for whom this
seems to have positive effects.
- So this, this is the lay of the land.
We talked about some of the darkness.
Lobotomies and so on. There
is some talk therapy ideas of
psychoanalysis, and then there
is, from the clinical psychology
side, cognitive behavioral therapy. Then
starts to emerge the psychopharmacology-
...that challenges this whole
shebang of talk therapy,
period. And can you talk about the
accidental origins of psychopharmacology-
...that challenges this whole thing?
- Hardly anybody had conceived of
the idea that drugs could be
used to treat mental illness.
Drugs had been used in the mental
hospitals back in the 19th and
20th centuries, but they were
usually things that were used
to control patients, to calm
them down. Opiates, for
example various hypnotics
that would put people
to sleep when they were extremely agitated,
and so forth. Sometimes marijuana was
experimented with, as was alcohol
in the 19th century interestingly
enough- ... given the revival of
psychedelics. But the idea that a drug might
be used to actually attack
the underlying problem,
it emerged by accident in the following
kind of way. The drug industry in general
Had emerged
mostly in Germany, where I'd mentioned
the most advanced medicine was being
practiced in the late
19th century. From the
chemical industry from, for example,
refining coal tar into different substances,
that's where we got aspirin. That's
where we got a whole bunch of drugs.
And gradually, the drug companies
become more organized. They
differentiate themselves from all the quack
remedies that are around. And the war,
I think greatly accelerates--
Again World War II
greatly accelerates things, not
least because we discover a
real magic bullet called
penicillin and then the other
antibiotics that we
subsequently come across.
Penicillin had been observed
by Alexander Fleming in
his, famously, in his
lab in some Petri tube
Petri dishes where bacteria
had been killed. Later was one
of the co-winners of the Nobel Prize
and made a lot of capital out of that
discovery. It was really Howard
Florey and his team at Oxford
who developed the therapeutic
potential of penicillin.
And actually, Florey flew
some of it in his jacket
across the Atlantic to America, and it was
Americans that solved the critical thing.
It took Florey and his team weeks to
develop enough penicillin to treat a single
mouse. What America learned how to do
was mass produce penicillin. And that
was critical because it was
vital to the war effort
obviously. And after the war, it was vital
to the civilian population because it
was such an important breakthrough.
So drugs, drug companies
grew fatter on that. They
embarked on research to try to find new
substances they could use to treat things.
Um, and a French company
named Rhône-Poulenc
came across a chemical that had
actually been synthesized back in the
1880s in Germany. It was an antihistamine,
chlorpromazine. They didn't know
what to do with it, but other
kinds of antihistamines in the
war had been used effectively,
and they thought "Well, let's look and see
if we can find a market for this drug."
And so they... The interesting
thing to remember in
those days is that investigating
the property of new drugs was
a Wild West phenomenon. There
were no controls. You could
do whatever you wanted, and
you handed stuff out and said,
"Why don't you try this and see
if it works?" Right? So Rhône-
Poulenc did that. They
thought this might work as an
antiemetic. If you have a
child who's prone to car
sickness, you give them
an antiemetic drug.
So that was one possibility. Another
possibility, it might work for
eczema so that people didn't scratch
themselves. Well, there were a
number of possibilities and somebody
said, "Well maybe it will work as
an anesthetic potentiator,"
meaning if you gave
some of these you need to use less
anesthetic or would act like a
catalyst because it tended
to make you sleepy. If you
read the leaflets on Dramamine,
one of the cautions is 'it'll
make you sleepy, don't drive,' right? So
why don't we give it to some surgeons
and see if they can find a use for it?
Literally it's like that. And one of
the people who gets that drug is a
lieutenant in the French
Navy, Henri Laborit,
and he tries it as an anesthetic
potentiator and he also gives it to some
of the patients who are awaiting surgery.
Normally when you're awaiting surgery,
you're a little bit anxious. These
patients stop being anxious.
Um, this was the era of
lobotomies and he wrote to
one of his relatives who worked in one of
the Paris mental hospitals. He said, "This
like, this works like a chemical
lobotomy. These people don't care
anymore about their surgery."
- And that's supposed to
be a good thing, right?
- Well, lobotomy hadn't become the nasty
word it would become in a few years.
So one of his colleagues
contacts Delay and Deniker, who
work at Saint-Anne's which is the biggest
mental hospital in Paris and says,
"Hey guys this might work on your
psychiatric patients. You should
give it a try." And they do.
When it doesn't work, they give larger dose
and when it doesn't work they give a large
dose and sure enough patients
stopped acting out. They stopped
smashing furniture. They
become-- They're still sorta conscious
but they're less mobile and they're
much calmer. And this is
why in the early stages
Chlorpromazine which becomes
known as Largactil or
Mighty Drug in Europe and Thorazine here,
it becomes known as a major
tranquilizer because it has this
tranquilizing effect. The
hospitals see it as a boon
because it'll help control the patients.
They're not yet thinking of it
as more than that. So that's
the accidental way it, way it's
discovered. It comes to
North America via Quebec,
where there's a
psychiatrist up there Heinz
Lehmann who actually works in the
Protestant Hospital. Québec in those
days is dominated by its Anglo
speaking elite who oppressed
the French Canadians pretty mightily
But because of the French connection,
he gets amounts of the drug.
Rhône-Poulenc has had to sell the
rights to an American company.
In those days, American physicians
don't trust European science or
European medicine-- especially
European medicine. So
Rhône-Poulenc sells the rights.
The first two drug companies it
approaches say, "No thank you. This
doesn't look very interesting to us. I
don't think there's much of a market."
And then SmithKline & French buys it
up and within two years, two million
people are taking this drug. It's a
bonanza for them right?
Not an accident 'cause
they put their best salesman
on the job of selling this
and they realize the hospital
psychiatrists mostly aren't
interested. They haven't yet
gotten to this idea of a chemical
cure or a chemical treatment.
- So it's the companies
that wake up to this?
- The companies wake up, they sell it to the
politicians. They go to the
state legislatures. They have
moving pictures of an agitated
patient who turns calm, you know.
- So this is already the
mechanism of big pharma?
- Yeah. So it's starting to be big
pharma. It transforms Smith Kline
& French from a small operator into a
big company, and then of course once
that's successful, it turns
out that chlorpromazine can
be easily tweaked as a molecule, and so
copycat drugs emerge on the
scene. So this happens in
America in 1954. The
following year in 1955
we get the so-called minor tranquilizers
being invented and brought to market.
- This is Miltown.
- Yeah, this is Miltown heavily
promoted by the first
major television star of
the mid-'50s Milton Berle,
who calls himself Uncle Miltown and
promotes the drug heavily on his show.
- So these are mostly like
tranquilizer type of effects?
- Those work really-- They're muscle
relaxant types of things and
later on in the '60s we
get Valium and Librium
coming on adding to or
replacing those, those first
generation drugs. So you have
major tranquilizers, minor
tranquilizers. Minor tranquilizers
and guess what? The Freudians don't want
really anything to do with these drugs.
- Right. Of course.
- Uh, the hospital psychiatrist
wants to wake up to the
usefulness of Thorazine and its analogues
do start using the drugs a lot,
And that's really important,
and in the early '60s,
they changed their name. Instead
of being major tranquilizers, they
become antipsychotics.
- Right.
- So that suggests they actually
attack the underlying psychosis.
- Is there any evidence of that for them?
- They do change the forms of psychosis
in important ways, some good
and some they fail to attack. So, um,
they reduce the agitation, they reduce
the delusions and the hallucinations, the
things psychiatrists call the positive
symptoms of schizophrenia
those, those they help
with for not every patient
but for a significant
number of patients, and they're
very -- That's very important.
- Why are they called the positive?
- The positive symptoms activate
things. They activate
the hallucinations and the
delusions. Those are changing,
and they're visible usually because if
somebody's deluded or hallucinating,
you know about it pretty quickly... right?
The negative symptoms are things like
apathy, loss of ability to interact
with people, poverty of language,
lack of initiative. All of
those things are devastating.
- Just to state out loud and clear that both
positive and negative affects so-called
by psychologists of schizophrenia are
both devastating and both negative.
- Yes, yes. Uh, I think that's right.
- In the common parlance
of what negative means.
- It's a very strange choice of language,
but it's been there for a long time,
so it's embedded. Now, to the extent
antipsychotics work, they work on the positive
symptoms.
They either dull them down so you're still
hallucinating a bit and you're still
delusional, but it's not--
it's very much less,
and you are you're somewhat pacified.
You're less overtly disturbed.
But the negative side of things,
not so much or not at all.
Then on top of that, the drugs work for
some people and they don't work for
others, and a significant number of psychotic
patients that are non-drug responders
just as a significant number of people
with depression are not responsive to
antidepressants. Moreover, initially
the enthusiasm for these drugs
everybody neglects the fact that
they have serious side effects or
many of them argue the side effects
are an essential part of the
treatment and you just have to put up
with it. So what are we talking about
when I say there are nasty side effects?
Well among others, you may
become incurably restless.
So you're constantly in motion, you're
moving around, you're never, never
still. If you're in the
presence of somebody
like that, it becomes unbearable
after a fairly short while, and
it's unbearable often to the
person who can't control it.
Other patients develop
Parkinson's disease symptoms.
Is an awful affliction which
unfortunately affects a
significant number of people each
year, and we don't have-- We have
through L-DOPA a means to delay its impact
but eventually that loses its efficacy
and unfortunately we don't have a cure
So you have those. And then
perhaps the nastiest is what's
called tardive dyskinesia.
Tardive because it's late developing,
it doesn't happen right away,
and dyskinesia because what
involves is jerky uncontrolled
movements of the body and particularly
of the facial muscles. So
your tongue will protrude, you'll
make strange noises, you'll
twitch, you'll stagger about walking. If
somebody like that is walking down the
street towards you, you will think
there's a mentally ill person and you'll
cross to the other side of the street. And
yes, they probably are a mentally
ill person but what you're seeing
is the iatrogenic effects
of the drugs they're on.
Okay? So that problem was ignored for
about 20 years. A paper appeared
in Science by George Crane,
a Maryland psychiatrist, in which he said,
"We as a profession have been
ignoring this terrible problem."
Yes, the drugs do some good, but
they're also creating a lot of harm,
and we need to focus more on that. And
it took a few years, but by the '80s,
I think the American Psychiatric Association
was very worried by that problem.
And um, the drug companies were kind of
worried about it, but didn't have any obvious
solution till towards the end of the '80s
something happened. Nineteen fifty-seven
when the people were developing
copycat versions of Thorazine,
clozapine was developed by a small
company which was subsequently bought
up by a bigger company and introduced
in Europe. It never came to America
because of two things. First, it tended
not to produce tardive dyskinesia,
and at that time many in the profession
thought if you didn't get those symptoms
you weren't attacking the
problem. Bizarre, right?
Secondly in a significant
number of patients
it destroyed the patient's white
blood cells and they died.
Okay? Not a good outcome.
So it was quickly withdrawn
from the market, and it never made it
to this side of the Atlantic. However,
as this tardive dyskinesia problem became
more acute, there was an attempt to revive
clozapine, and it turns out
it tends to work better in
treatment-resistant cases, meaning
cases that don't respond to the
other antipsychotics that we have.
And it could be revived but at
the cost of weekly blood checks
'cause you had to be very
careful if your white blood
cells count started to
drop, you had to stop.
Right? So it came to
market in the late '80s,
and very quickly other drug companies
tried to find other compounds
actually chemically not related
to it, but that's hardly the
point. The whole class of drugs became
known as second generation antipsychotics.
- So Clozapine, Risperdal--
- Yes, those kinds of ones.
- Zyprexa.
- Zyprexa among others.
- Yes. And so there were a number
of these, and they have actually
-- Because they are chemically quite
different from each other, but they're
classed together in the public mind and -
...in the professional mind.
They tend to have different side
effect profiles and slightly different
modes of action and differing
levels of efficacy, I think.
- Of course, there's not a real,
at that time or even now, a real science
of like when you have a human come to you,
what is the actual protocol of
how you figure out which to give?
- Right. So in 2005 most of the-- I should
say, once the Drugs Revolution
came along, increasingly
the studies were funded by the drug
companies who owned the data and
controlled the data--
- Right
- ...and only released what they chose to
release, what was helpful for them and
not what wasn't.
- And they were heavily marketing stuff.
- Oh yeah, very heavily mar-- And then, to
get FDA approval of efficacy and safety you
needed two trials.
You might have conducted 15 trials
and 13 of them had been failures,
but if you had two that worked,
that was enough. That's what you
needed. That was the gold standard. So
2005, National Institutes of Mental Health
funds this drug study,
not an industry study,
and what it wants to look at,
the first generation drugs are
now out of patent and they're
cheap. The second generation are
patented and are quite expensive, ten
times as expensive in some cases.
So we do something called
the CATIE Study, and it's
published in the New England Journal
of Medicine. And there are two
interesting findings. So you
have one first generation
antipsychotic, one of those
very early drugs, and you
have four more recent drugs
that you're looking at.
And you ask a number of
questions. Are the new drugs more
efficacious than the old drug? No.
Hmm. Were patients willing to
tolerate these drugs? And that was a
finding that I thought was much
underreported at the time. Between 67% and
82% of the patients, depending
on which drug they were on,
dropped out of the trial because either the
drug wasn't working or they couldn't stand
the side effects. So that
tells you, these are our
best drugs, you know, there
are real complications here.
And then as we delve further into it,
do they have nasty side effects? Well,
less tardive dyskinesia somewhat, but a
whole new set of side effects. If you take
these pills, you will gain, in
most cases, a lot of weight,
10, 20, 30, 40 pounds, 50 pounds. What
does that do? That gives
you metabolic syndrome;
it gives you diabetes; it
gives you heart trouble. So
important to state when
we're looking at this 'cause
there is no-- There is no free lunch
with medicine. If you take an aspirin,
it may cause your stomach
to bleed, sometimes enough
to really put you in serious
jeopardy. Most of the time it's fine.
Um, everything... Every drug that's
brought to market has the main
effect we're looking for and
some side effects which may be
minimal for most people but for some people
maybe worse than that. So we've got to--
It's one of these cost-benefit
analyses, right? You--
You're getting some relief from your
psychiatric symptoms, but
you're courting these other
dangers that may or may not
arise, and going in, we don't
know where you're gonna fall.
We don't know; trial and error.
- You mean every individual that walks into
the picture, they don't know where on
distribution they fall?
- Right. And we have no biological markers
at the moment that would tell us.
One or two of my friends in the,
um, psychiatric genetics industry,
uh, if that's the right term for it,
but, you know, in that research area
are saying, "Well, we haven't done
very well to find the genetic
roots of mental illness," but maybe we can
learn to distinguish which patients are
gonna respond well to drugs and which
will, which shouldn't be given them
because they're not going to. Um,
that's a promissory note. It's not
something that they actually can do now.
It's just we hope we'll be able to do this,
and I hope they're able to do it too. But
You know, you can't have an enormous
amount of confidence in that. Maybe
it'll happen, or maybe some
other mechanism will emerge that
allows us to see who the
responders and nonresponders are.
Who's gonna suffer the worst side effects
if they're put on these medications? And
The side effects do vary, so, um,
though a lot of what I've described is
common to this class of drugs.
- And sometimes it's hard to describe the
side effect. You're talking about the human
mind. Yeah, yeah. So describing the
side effects, it's not like ble-
bleeding or like diarrhea or-
- Well, yeah.
- Weight gain, that's describable, but
like the effect on your personality...
- Yep, that's much harder, much harder. People,
you know, some of the patients who drop
out drop out because they find
the richness of their mental life is
completely gone, and they don't want
to tolerate that. They'd sooner tolerate
some hallucinations. That's a hard one.
- So there's a that picture, the
SSRIs that also came to be
Prozac, Zoloft, Paxil during
that time. Yes, Paxil, all of
that. Well again, they're the second
generation of antidepressants.
Mm-hmm. So that's a complicated
story. Again, it's an
accident. They're at treating
patients with advanced
tuberculosis in the 1950s. Now, that's a
very unpleasant thing that's also gonna kill
you, so tuberculosis, very
advanced cases. You're coughing your lungs
up. You're depressed as all get out.
And here we have two new
drugs, Iprsoltanto we can
use that maybe will treat the condition
when you give it to the patients, and
these depressed tuberculosis patients
start acting happy, dancing about. Their
mood changes. Bingo! We've got something
that maybe we can use over here to
treat depression. However,
the drug companies in circa
1960 think of depression as a small market
because what they're talking about is the
kind of melancholic psychotic
depressions that leads people
into the mental hospital. And that's not an
insignificant group, but it's not a huge
group. So it's really much later on that things
begin to change. Right now, it's fair to say
Depression is the common cold of psychiatry.
It's, you know, it's abundant there, the
depressive diagnosis, probably the most
commonly given among psychiatrists, so part of
that is a deeper understanding of the
human mind, and a big part of that is
probably the drug companies
convincing the world.
- Well, it's transforming, yes.
So, there were big disputes for
example, when DSM-5 was being
contemplated about whether grief,
bereavement would count as a mental disorder,
as count as a form of depression if you
lose a parent, if you lose,
even worse, a child, um
It's a deeply-- how can I put
it? Deeply upsetting, yes.
Some psychiatrists say yes and some no,
but it's an example of what happens
in psychiatry, repeatedly, what
I would call diagnostic creep,
which is a term, actually, an
Australian named Nick Haslam came
up with. But it's a phenomenon
I described before that. You
start with a core of unambiguous
deviations from the norm
that are so serious that any
competent member of the
culture knows that's that. But
then it-- you begin to say, "Well,
there's this penumbra," you see, and
just outside that core, there are people
who are also disturbed, not perhaps as
sufficiently disturbed that you
actually recognize it, but it's
happening. And so that has tended to happen
over and over again. Parents with an
autistic child won't
necessarily agree with what I'm
about to say, but the
chief editor of DSM-IV,
Allen Frances, is convinced the
huge increase in the number of
diagnoses of autism is more driven by the
fact he loosened the criteria
for the diagnosis than it is
because there are more actual
cases. Autism used to be a fairly
rare phenomenon, and now sadly it's
a very broad one. And I understand
why parents react very
negatively to that because the
diagnosis is the key to all
sorts of social supports and
educational supports and all the
rest, and they're dealing with a
child who is extremely difficult. But
there is a real difference between
the most severe forms of
autism where people lose
capacity to speak and
very often any ability to
interact with other people and so forth,
and the other cases that are of
a still serious but milder sort.
Diagnostic creep is not driven just by
psychiatric imperialism, the desire
for more territory, more patients.
It's driven as well by
patients and people and,
and they resist it being
pushed back very often.
So families have formed
organizations like NAMI, but
those aren't the mentally ill. Those are the
family members of the mentally ill, and there
are differences in the perspectives
and the interests of the family
members and the patients- ...
And that's easy to forget.
- I think one of the things
you talk about is,
uh, I mean, the quote you had
was use the word madness.
But that madness or
mental health maladies,
if you're suffering from them,
it's a deeply lonely experience.
And then if you're around somebody suffering
from it, it's a very social experience.
- Yeah. Yeah, this is actually --
that's a paraphrase of -- I was
quoting one of my friends and fellow
historians of psychiatry, Michael
MacDonald. The most solitary of
afflictions for the sufferer and the
most social of maladies for those
around them. And there's lots of
ways in which you can see
that very powerfully, and that's why
I think there are a ton of people who
suffer in various ways from, from mental
disturbances of one sort and another.
But the effects aren't confined
to them. They extend out
to everybody else around
them, and that's really
powerful. So we had this
first generation there were
actually two different
kinds of antidepressants,
MAOIs as they're called in the trade, and
tricyclics which were called
tricyclics 'cause they had a
third ring of a certain
element in their molecule.
Those had as I say, a limited market, but
also there were complications
associated with
them that it was easy to
overdose and die. And so
giving a depressed patient a bunch
of pills that if they took too many
of them would kill them was
tricky. They also could
kill you another way because for
example, you couldn't -- certain dietary
items, cheese, cured meats,
in combination with them were very, very
health threatening, maybe even fatal.
Now, in the late '80s,
the drug companies came across
a new class of antidepressants
that didn't have those side effects.
As we'll see, they had other side
effects, but not those. And
the most famous of those
was Prozac. There were
a class of drugs called
SSRIs, and again forgive the
acronyms, but what it means is
selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors.
Serotonin is something manufactured
in our bodies, actually
in our digestive system, and
it performs a variety of
functions in the body. But it's also one
of the neurotransmitters in our brains.
And the way these drugs worked was by
slowing the reuptake of serotonin
in the brain, which was
marketed by the drug companies as the
solution to depression. That
when you got depressed,
it was because you didn't have enough
serotonin in your brain, and these pills
solved that problem. It was like, well,
Tipper Gore, Al Gore's ex-wife, was like many
politicians' wives, depressed
for reasons I fully understand
or at least partially understand. And she
went to her psychiatrist and that
was one of the things she was given,
and she became one of the big
public advocates for SSRIs which
still are the most
prescribed antidepressants.
- Do they work? And what
are the side effects?
- Yeah. So here's where we get
into slippery territory. Every
time you do a controlled study
of these antidepressants,
they beat placebo in a
statistically significant margin,
but not necessarily in a
clinically significant margin.
And this is when you see drug
ads, be very careful. This one
significantly improves X or Y.
Does that mean clinically or does
it mean statistically? Because
the fact-- if you -- when
we measure improvement with
depression, we tend to use
rating scales of various sorts.
And if you improve on one of the major
scales that's used by one or two points
on a 60-point scale, it
may be enough to show
statistical significance. These drugs
look a little better than placebo,
but doesn't really affect your quality
of life much. And for most patients,
antidepressants are marginally better
than placebo, but a lot of the
effect is the placebo effect.
And they come with very difficult side
effects. A lot of people describe them as
numbing drugs. They--
...flatten everything out,
So you can't experience the
highs and lows that normally
we take as part of human
experience. And then, um,
the numbing extends elsewhere in
your body. In particular, lots
of patients find a complete
loss of libido. They...
They can't get an erection.
They can't climax if they're a
woman. Their sex life just goes away,
and sometimes it doesn't come
back after you stop the drugs.
Next layer of problems, getting off
the drugs for some people turns
out to be hell on wheels. They get worse
depression than they had before. They
get a feel-- uh, terrible feelings. Their
brain is sparking something's wrong.
And so many patients find themselves
trapped on those drugs for
a long time, and we don't know what
the effects of that are gonna be.
So it's a very mixed picture,
you know. That's why I
think groups like NICE
in England are saying,
"Use CBT as the first line,
not drugs." But again,
it's also fair to say, I think
what we find and there was a
recent Lancet study that I think
was revealing on this point.
It's like this with both antipsychotics
and antidepressants. You have
a group of people who respond
pretty well, and the side
effects for them are bearable or even
they don't experience them. That's great.
You have a group of people, and it's
significant. With depressed patients,
we're talking 40 or north of forty
percent who aren't responding. Okay?
So drugs aren't doing anything for
them, and they're running a risk.
And then in the middle, you have a
group of people who get some positive
improvement, but they also get side
effects, and that's where, you know, this
cost-benefit analysis, if we can call
it that, comes into play, and it's
very difficult. And the
problem is going in,
you don't know which group
you're gonna fall in.
And your, and your doctor doesn't know
which group you're gonna fall in. And
more importantly, one of the things
the Drugs Revolution did was it moved
the diagnosis and the
prescribing of things
away from psychiatry
alone, so many of these
things, particularly antidepressants,
are dispensed by primary
care docs, not psychiatrists.
- Let's zoom out. We did say
that there's a real crisis.
From an individual perspective suffering
from psychosis or suffering from
depression- ... What are
you supposed to do? What
works, and what is the hope for the
future in the next ten, twenty out?
- So you probably need to try the drugs
because the suffering is very intense.
But you need to be aware of things,
and you need a clinician who's
monitoring very carefully. More generally,
psychiatric research needs to broaden.
We have spent all our monies on drugs,
on neuroscience, and on
genetics, but there are
other things we could do
that would improve the lives
of families and patients more immediately.
So we need to spend some time on the
psychosocial dimensions of
mental illness and to allow
psychiatrists to build careers in those
fields. One of the problems if you're an
academic psychiatrist, your whole
future is dependent on you
bringing in grant monies,
and there aren't grant monies
available to study: Are there better
ways we could cope with the problem
of homelessness? Are there better
ways we could ease the problem for
families who are having to cope
with somebody in their
midst who's hallucinating?
That sort of thing, I think, would help.
- What about talk therapy on both
the CBT, cognitive behavioral
therapy, and psychoanalysis?
We left psychoanalysis in this
place where society left it behind.
- I think it's become a
niche product now. Only,
only the very wealthy can afford
to do it, and some of them
indeed do make use of it, and some
of them claim that it helps them.
- Oh, do you think there's future
in it? I will add an extra-- I
would add an extra bit to that. Carefully
is with the advent and the rapid
improvement of artificial
intelligence systems-
...that are able to communicate with
individual humans and learn a lot about them,
and have a conversation about
the deepest secrets that you
sometimes actually would even be
uncomfortable telling even a therapist.
That starts to go into the realm of
Freud and Jung and psychoanalysis.
- Well, yes, and we did see actually COVID
with the isolation that it produced and
the fact people couldn't go to their
therapists directly. We did see
the rise of some of this distant
learning of this, and some of
it may indeed be mechanizable
in the way you described.
It's very important
that psychiatrists broaden
their perspective on
these things, and some
already have. I think
public policy is in a mess when it
comes to serious mental illness,
but I'm pessimistic about fixing that
'cause it would cost bunches of money.
If we were talking about something
where we could cure people,
transform them from, as they used
to say, tax eaters to taxpayers,
there'd be incentive to do it.
But the honest answer is right
now that's not where we are. And so we
face dilemmas. I think helping people as
much as we can with social supports --And,
you know, social interaction
is tremendously important to
people's mental health. If they lack it,
if they're lonely, if they're isolated,
it does bad things to people. So somehow
providing that kind of support, providing
some sense of agency to
people who often lack it
would be very helpful.
Uh, I hope somebody has a
breakthrough and produces
a better drug because
unlike some people, I would be
astonished if the major forms
of mental illness didn't have a
biological component to them.
I don't think that's ever gonna be the
whole story, but it's going to be an
important part of the story,
and therefore, you know, the
fact that major drug companies have
abandoned research in this area,
they've been bad actors in
many ways, but the drugs have
had some positive effects, and
the fact that there's no research
being done by the people with the most
money to develop better treatments is well,
one word for it would be depressing.
You know? That's not what we wanna see.
- So the path forward is a mix- ....of
continued research on drugs, but from a
patient perspective, extreme
caution in use of those drugs.
Uh, talk therapy, whether
it's CBT or psychoanalysis,
further investigation research on
that front. Then the psychosocial
component of social family-
.....people around you, less
loneliness, investigating how
from a cultural social perspective and
from a public policy perspective, can we
increase the amount of social
connections that people who
suffer have and all of that together?
- Yes. And breakthrough with
people who have a very hard time
making those connections or who've
lost the ability to make them.
- If we can zoom out,
looking back at this rich history of
human beings, and we did look at the
darkness, but I think there's
a very large number of people
that want to help those who suffer. So,
looking at the history of
people trying to figure out-
how to help those who suffer, what gives
you hope about our future? A real hope
for the future of psychiatry that we
can actually help people who suffer.
- Well, I think we have a profession
with many very well-meaning people
who see the suffering on a
day-to-day, face-to-face basis.
And I like to think that
among them will be people who
move this thing forward.
And the fact is we
have moved things forward. We
have tended to dwell a lot on
some of the very unsavory
aspects of the past,
and even some of the drawbacks of what
we have available to us in the present.
But it is important to see at times
highly motivated people have
been able to do very good
things to help people with
these conditions. And there is,
I think, hope in the future
that we will see more of that,
Than has been the case. And that
involves, in some senses, a shift in the
mentality of a whole
profession in, in a more
caring kind of direction or less
technocratic kind of direction, less
reliance on something as simple as giving
people pills, because that can help,
but it's clearly not gonna be
the solution to the whole thing.
We need a system that is
aware of and catering to the,
suffering that people experience
and finds ways, if they
can't eliminate it entirely, to
ameliorate it in ways that people will
sense is actually of help
to them. It's a, it's a
very difficult area,
this one. It's one that,
touches some of the most profound
aspects of ourselves as human beings
and I think as difficult
as this problem is
it's very important not to be
cynical. Not to give up hope,
not to deny the possibility of progress,
because that's always
there. And has happened and
I hope will happen with increasing
pace in the years ahead of us.
- And if you're listening to these words
and you're right now in this moment of your
life where you yourself are suffering,
please know we're with you. We're
in this together. Stay strong.
There's hope. Legitimately, as one
human to another, I love you. Brother,
sister, if you're listening
to this, stay strong.
Andrew, thank you for this incredible
work of history that you do.
Incredible work of raising
awareness, stepping into a
difficult topic, and trying to
find the wisdom, the insights
in it. And thank you for this
incredible conversation today.
- Lex, thank you for having me, and
I felt you were remarkably
prepared to push me in various
directions. So you'd
obviously done a lot of
preparation to get this in
the right frame. And I hope,
that people will get something positive
from this conversation along with
some of the darkness we've inevitably
had to talk about.
- Thank you for listening to this conversation with
Andrew Scull. To support this podcast, please
check out our sponsors in the description,
where you can also find links to contact me,
ask questions, give
feedback, and so on. And
now let me leave you with some words from
Friedrich Nietzsche: "To live is to suffer,
To survive is to find
meaning in the suffering."
Thank you for listening, and
I hope to see you next time.